<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc>
<rfc xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" ipr="pre5378Trust200902" submissionType="IETF" category="std" xml:lang="en" consensus="true" docName="draft-ietf-calext-jscontact-13" obsoletes="" updates="" tocInclude="true" symRefs="true" sortRefs="true" version="3">
  <!-- xml2rfc v2v3 conversion 3.6.0 -->
  <front>
    <title abbrev="JSContact">JSContact: A JSON representation of contact data</title>
    <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-ietf-calext-jscontact-13"/>
    <author initials="R." surname="Stepanek" fullname="Robert Stepanek">
      <organization>Fastmail</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>PO Box 234, Collins St West</street>
          <city>Melbourne</city>
          <code>VIC 8007</code>
          <country>Australia</country>
          <region> </region>
        </postal>
        <email>rsto@fastmailteam.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author initials="M." surname="Loffredo" fullname="Mario Loffredo">
      <organization>IIT-CNR</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Via Moruzzi,1</street>
          <city>Pisa</city>
          <code>56124</code>
          <country>Italy</country>
          <region> </region>
        </postal>
        <email>mario.loffredo@iit.cnr.it</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <date year="2023" month="July" day="24"/>
    <area>Applications</area>
    <workgroup>Calendaring Extensions</workgroup>
    <keyword>JSON</keyword>
    <keyword>addressbook</keyword>
    <keyword>contacts</keyword>
    <keyword>cards</keyword>
    <keyword>VCARD</keyword>
    <abstract>
      <t>This specification defines a data model and JSON representation of contact card information that can be used for data storage and exchange in address book or directory applications.  It aims to be an alternative to the vCard data format and to be unambiguous, extendable and simple to process.  In contrast to the JSON-based jCard format, it is not a direct mapping from the vCard data model and expands semantics where appropriate.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>
  <middle>
    <section anchor="introduction" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Introduction</name>
      <t>This document defines a data model for contact card data normally used in address book or directory applications and services.  It aims to be an alternative to the vCard data format <xref target="RFC6350" format="default"/>.</t>
      <t>The key design considerations for this data model are as follows:</t>
      <ul spacing="normal">
        <li>The data model and set of attributes should mostly be compatible with the one defined for the vCard data format <xref target="RFC6350" format="default"/> and extensions (<xref target="RFC6473" format="default"/>, <xref target="RFC6474" format="default"/>, <xref target="RFC6715" format="default"/>, <xref target="RFC6869" format="default"/>, <xref target="RFC8605" format="default"/>).  The specification should add new attributes or value types where appropriate. Not all existing vCard definitions need an equivalent in JSContact, especially if the vCard definition is considered to be obsolete or otherwise inappropriate.  Conversion between the data formats need not fully preserve semantic meaning.</li>
        <li>The attributes of the card data represented must be described as simple key-value pairs, reducing complexity of their representation.</li>
        <li>The data model should avoid all ambiguities and make it difficult to make mistakes during implementation.</li>
        <li>Extensions, such as new properties and components, <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> lead to requiring an update to this document.</li>
      </ul>
      <t>The representation of this data model is defined in the I-JSON format <xref target="RFC7493" format="default"/>, which is a strict subset of the JavaScript Object Notation (JSON) Data Interchange Format <xref target="RFC8259" format="default"/>.  Using JSON is mostly a pragmatic choice: its widespread use makes JSContact easier to adopt, and the availability of production-ready JSON implementations eliminates a whole category of parser-related interoperability issues.</t>
      <section anchor="relation-to-vcard" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Motivation and Relation to vCard, jCard and xCard</name>
        <t>The vCard data format <xref target="RFC6350"/> is an interchange format for contacts data between address book service providers and vendors.  However, this format has gone through multiple specifications iterations with only a subset of its deprecated <xref target="RFC2426">version 3</xref> being widely in use.  Consequently, products and services internally use a richer contact data model than they expose when serializing that information to vCard.  In addition, service providers often use a proprietary JSON representation of contact data in their APIs.</t>
        <t>JSContact provides a standard JSON-based data model and representation of contact data as an alternative to proprietary formats.</t>
        <t>While writing this document, several features missing in vCard were brought to the attention of the authors, such as social media contacts, gender pronouns and others.  This highlights how vCard is not perceived as an evolving format and consequently hasn't been updated since close to ten years.  JSContact addresses these unmet demands and defines new vCard properties and parameters to allow interchanging them in both formats.</t>
        <t>The xCard <xref target="RFC6351" format="default"/> and jCard <xref target="RFC7095" format="default"/> specifications define alternative representations for vCard data, in XML and JSON format respectively.  Both explicitly aim to not change the underlying data model.  Accordingly, they are regarded as equal to vCard in the context of this document.</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="notational-conventions" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Notational Conventions</name>
        <t>The key words "<bcp14>MUST</bcp14>", "<bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14>", "<bcp14>REQUIRED</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHALL</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHALL NOT</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHOULD NOT</bcp14>", "<bcp14>RECOMMENDED</bcp14>", "<bcp14>NOT RECOMMENDED</bcp14>", "<bcp14>MAY</bcp14>", and "<bcp14>OPTIONAL</bcp14>" in this document are to be interpreted as described in BCP 14 <xref target="RFC2119" format="default" sectionFormat="of" derivedContent="RFC2119"/> <xref target="RFC8174" format="default" sectionFormat="of" derivedContent="RFC8174"/> when, and only when, they appear in all capitals, as shown here.</t>
        <t>The ABNF definitions in this document use the notations of <xref target="RFC5234"/>. ABNF rules not defined in this document either are defined in <xref target="RFC5234"/> (such as the ABNF for CRLF, WSP, DQUOTE, VCHAR, ALPHA, and DIGIT) or <xref target="RFC6350"/>.</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="data-type-notations">
        <name>Data Type Notations</name>
        <t>This section introduces the notations and terminology used to define data types in JSContact.</t>
        <t>The underlying format for JSContact is JSON and so also its data types build on JSON values.  The terms "object" and "array" as well as the four primitive types ("strings", "numbers", "booleans", and "null") are to be interpreted as described in <xref target="RFC8259" section="1"/>.  All JSContact data <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be valid according to the constraints given in <xref target="RFC7493">I-JSON</xref>.  Unless otherwise noted, all member names in JSON objects and all string values are case sensitive.  Within context of JSON objects, the term "key" is synonymous with "member name" as defined in <xref target="RFC8259" section="1"/>.</t>
        <section anchor="objects-and-properties" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>Objects and Properties</name>
          <t>JSContact defines data types for contact information such as addresses or names.  This information typically consists of multiple related elements, for example a personal name and surname together form a name.  These related elements are organized in JSContact objects.  A JSContact object is a JSON object which:</t>
          <ol>
            <li>Has a unique type name registered in the <xref target="iana-type-registry">IANA JSContact Types Registry</xref>.</li>
            <li>Has one or more object members for which the name and allowed value types are specified.  Such members are called "properties".</li>
            <li>Has one property named <tt>@type</tt> with a string value that matches the type name of this JSContact object.  In general, this property does not need to be set explicitly as outlined in <xref target="prop-type"/>.</li>
          </ol>
          <t>The following sections specify how to define JSContact object types. <xref target="validating-jscontact"/> and <xref target="vendor-specific-extensions"/> then define the exact requirements for property names.</t>
          <t>The next paragraph illustrates how a JSContact object is defined:</t>
          <blockquote>
            <t>A Foo object has the following properties:</t>
            <ul>
              <li><tt>qux</tt>: Number (mandatory).  Defines the qux-ishness of this contact.  The value <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be an integer greater than 0 and less than 10.</li>
            </ul>
          </blockquote>
          <t>Here, a JSContact object type named <tt>Foo</tt> is defined.  In addition to its <tt>@type</tt> property it has a property named <tt>qux</tt> for which values <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be valid according to the definition of the <tt>Number</tt> type.  The property has one attribute, <tt>mandatory</tt>, which specifies that the property <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be present for an instance of this JSContact object to be valid.  Finally, a free-text description describes the semantics and further restrictions.</t>
        </section>
        <section anchor="type-signatures" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>Type Signatures</name>
          <t>Type signatures are given for all JSON values and JSContact definitions in this document.  The following conventions are used:</t>
          <ul spacing="normal">
            <li><tt>String</tt> - The JSON string type.</li>
            <li><tt>Number</tt> - The JSON number type.</li>
            <li><tt>Boolean</tt> - The JSON boolean type.</li>
            <li><tt>A[B]</tt> - A JSON object where the keys are all of the type <tt>A</tt>, and the values are all of the type <tt>B</tt>.</li>
            <li><tt>A[]</tt> - A JSON array of values of type <tt>A</tt>.</li>
            <li><tt>A|B</tt> - The value is either of type <tt>A</tt> or of type <tt>B</tt>.</li>
            <li><tt>*</tt> - The type is undefined (the value could be any type, although permitted values may be constrained by the context of this value).</li>
          </ul>
          <t><xref target="common-data-types"/> defines common data types, including signed or unsigned integers and dates.</t>
        </section>
        <section anchor="property-attributes" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>Property Attributes</name>
          <t>Object properties may also have a set of attributes defined along with the type signature. These have the following meanings:</t>
          <ul>
            <li><tt>mandatory</tt>: The property <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be set for an instance of this object to be valid.</li>
            <li><tt>optional</tt>: The property can but not need be set for an instance of this object to be valid.</li>
            <li><tt>default</tt>: This is followed by a JSON value. That value will be used for this property if it is omitted.</li>
            <li><tt>defaultType</tt>: This is followed by the name of a JSContact object type.  A property value of JSContact object type is expected to be of this named type, in case it omits the <tt>@type</tt> property.</li>
          </ul>
        </section>
        <section anchor="prop-type" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>The <tt>@type</tt> Property</name>
          <t>This property is defined as:</t>
          <ul>
            <li><tt>@type</tt>: String.  Specifies the type of this object.  This <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> match the type name of the JSContact object of which this JSON object is an instance of.</li>
          </ul>
          <t>The purpose of this property is to help implementations identify which JSContact object type a given JSON object represents.  Implementations <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> validate that JSON objects with this property conform to the specification of the JSContact object type of that name.</t>
          <t>In many cases the <tt>@type</tt> property value is implied by where its object occurs in JSContact data. Assuming that both <tt>A</tt> and <tt>B</tt> are JSContact object types:</t>
          <ul>
            <li>An object that is set as the value for a property with type signature <tt>A</tt> <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> have the <tt>@type</tt> property set.  If the <tt>@type</tt> property is not set then its value is implied to be <tt>A</tt> by the property definition.</li>
            <li>An object that is set as the value for a property with type signature <tt>A|B (defaultType: A)</tt> <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> have the <tt>@type</tt> property set if it is an instance of <tt>A</tt>.  It <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> have the <tt>@type</tt> property set if it is an instance of <tt>B</tt>.  If instead the <tt>defaultType</tt> attribute is not defined then the <tt>@type</tt> property <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> also be set for <tt>A</tt>.</li>
            <li>An object that is not the value of a property, such at the root of JSON data (directly or as member of an array), <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> have the <tt>@type</tt> property set.</li>
          </ul>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section anchor="common-data-types" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Common Data Types</name>
        <t>In addition to the standard JSON data types, a couple of additional data types are common to the definitions of JSContact objects and properties.</t>
        <section anchor="id" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>Id</name>
          <t>Where <tt>Id</tt> is given as a data type, it means a <tt>String</tt> of at least 1 and a maximum of 255 octets in size, and it <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> only contain characters from the <tt>URL and Filename Safe</tt> base64url alphabet, as defined in Section 5 of <xref target="RFC4648" format="default"/>, excluding the pad character (<tt>=</tt>).  This means the allowed characters are the ASCII alphanumeric characters (<tt>A-Za-z0-9</tt>), hyphen (<tt>-</tt>), and underscore (<tt>_</tt>).</t>
          <t>In many places in JSContact a JSON map is used where the map keys are of type Id and the map values are all the same type of object.  This construction represents an unordered set of objects, with the added advantage that each entry has a name (the corresponding map key).  This allows for more concise patching of objects, and, when applicable, for the objects in question to be referenced from other objects within the JSContact object.  The map keys <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be preserved across multiple versions of the JSContact object.</t>
          <t>Unless otherwise specified for a particular property, there are no uniqueness constraints on an Id value (other than, of course, the requirement that you cannot have two values with the same key within a single JSON map).  For example, two <xref target="card">Card</xref> objects might use the same Ids in their respective <tt>photos</tt> properties.  Or within the same Card the same Id could appear in the <tt>emails</tt> and <tt>phones</tt> properties.  These situations do not imply any semantic connections among the objects.</t>
        </section>
        <section anchor="int-unsignedint" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>Int and UnsignedInt</name>
          <t>Where <tt>Int</tt> is given as a data type, it means an integer in the range -2<sup>53</sup>+1 &lt;= value &lt;= 2<sup>53</sup>-1, the safe range for integers stored in a floating-point double, represented as a JSON <tt>Number</tt>.</t>
          <t>Where <tt>UnsignedInt</tt> is given as a data type, it means an integer in the range 0 &lt;= value &lt;= 2<sup>53</sup>-1, represented as a JSON <tt>Number</tt>.</t>
        </section>
        <section anchor="patchobject" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>PatchObject</name>
          <t>A PatchObject is of type <tt>String[*]</tt>, and represents an unordered set of patches on a JSON object.
      Each key is a path represented in a subset of JSON pointer format <xref target="RFC6901"/>.  The paths have an implicit leading <tt>/</tt>, so each key is prefixed with <tt>/</tt> before applying the JSON pointer evaluation algorithm.</t>
          <t>A patch within a PatchObject is only valid if all the following conditions apply:</t>
          <ol>
            <li>The pointer <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> reference inside an array but if the last reference token in the pointer is an array index, then the patch value <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> be null.  The pointer <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> use "-" as an array index in any of its reference tokens (i.e., you <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> insert/delete from an array, but you <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> replace the contents of its existing members.  To add or remove members, one needs to replace the complete array value).</li>
            <li>All reference tokens prior to the last (i.e., the value after the final slash) <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> already exist as values in the object being patched.  If the last reference token is an array index, then a member at this index <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> already exist in the referenced array.</li>
            <li>There <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> be two patches in the PatchObject where the pointer of one is the prefix of the pointer of the other, e.g., <tt>addresses/1/city</tt> and <tt>addresses</tt>.</li>
            <li>The value for the patch <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be valid for the property being set (of the correct type and obeying any other applicable restrictions), or if null the property <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be optional.</li>
          </ol>
          <t>The value associated with each pointer determines how to apply that patch:</t>
          <ul>
            <li>If null, remove the property from the patched object.  If the key is not present in the parent, this a no-op.</li>
            <li>If non-null, set the value given as the value for this property (this may be a replacement or addition to the object being patched).</li>
          </ul>
          <t>A PatchObject does not define its own <xref target="prop-type"><tt>@type</tt></xref> property.  Instead, a <tt>@type</tt> property in a patch <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be handled as any other patched property value.</t>
          <t>Implementations <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> reject in its entirety a PatchObject if any of its patches are invalid.   Implementations <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> apply partial patches.</t>
        </section>
        <section anchor="resource" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>Resource</name>
          <t>This data type defines a resource associated with the entity represented by this Card, identified by a URI <xref target="RFC3986" format="default"/>.  Several property definitions later in this document refer to the Resource data type as the basis for their property-specific value types.  The Resource data type defines the properties that are common to all of them.  Property definitions making use of Resource <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> define additional properties for their value types.</t>
          <t>The <tt>@type</tt> property value <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> be <tt>Resource</tt>, instead it <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be the name of a concrete resource type (see <xref target="resource-properties"/>).  A Resource object has the following properties.</t>
          <ul spacing="normal">
            <li>
              <t>@type: <tt>String</tt>.  Specifies the type of this resource object.  The allowed value is defined in later sections of this document for each concrete resource type (<xref target="resource-properties"/>).</t>
            </li>
            <li>
              <t>kind: <tt>String</tt> (optional).
The kind of the resource.  The allowed values are defined in the property definition that makes use of the Resource type.  Some property definitions may change this property from being optional to mandatory.
</t>
            </li>
            <li>uri: <tt>String</tt> (mandatory).
The resource value.  This <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be a <em>URI</em> as defined in Section 3 of <xref target="RFC3986" format="default"/> and updates.</li>
            <li>mediaType: <tt>String</tt> (optional).
Used for URI resource values.  Provides the media type <xref target="RFC2046" format="default"/> of the resource identified by the URI.</li>
            <li>contexts: <tt>String[Boolean]</tt> (optional).
The contexts in which to use this resource.  Also see <xref target="prop-contexts"/>.</li>
            <li>pref: <tt>UnsignedInt</tt> (optional).
            The preference of this resource in relation to other resources.  Also see <xref target="prop-pref"/>.</li>
            <li>label: <tt>String</tt> (optional).
            A custom label for the value, see <xref target="prop-label"/>.</li>
          </ul>
        </section>
        <section anchor="utcdatetime" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>UTCDateTime</name>
          <t>This is a string in <xref target="RFC3339" format="default"/> <tt>date-time</tt> format, with the further restrictions that any letters <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be in uppercase, and the time offset <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be the character <tt>Z</tt>.  Fractional second values <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> be included unless non-zero and <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> have trailing zeros, to ensure there is only a single representation for each date-time.</t>
          <t>For example, <tt>2010-10-10T10:10:10.003Z</tt> is conformant, but <tt>2010-10-10T10:10:10.000Z</tt> is invalid and is correctly encoded as <tt>2010-10-10T10:10:10Z</tt>.</t>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section anchor="comon-properties">
        <name>Common Properties</name>
        <t>Most of the properties in this document are specific to a single JSContact object type.  Such properties are defined along with the respective object type.  The properties in this section are common to multiple data types and are defined here to avoid repetition.  Note that these properties <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> only be set for a JSContact object if they are explicitly mentioned to be allowed for this object type.</t>
        <section anchor="prop-contexts" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>contexts</name>
          <t>Type: <tt>String[Boolean]</tt></t>
          <t>This property associates contact information with one or more contexts in which it should be used.  For example, someone might have distinct phone numbers for work and private contexts, and may set the desired context on the respective phone number in the <xref target="phones"><tt>phones</tt></xref> property.</t>
          <t>This section defines common contexts.  Additional contexts may be defined in the properties or data types that make use of this property.  The <xref target="enumerated-values">enumerated</xref> common context values are:</t>
          <ul spacing="normal">
            <li><tt>private</tt>: The contact information may be used to contact in a private context.</li>
            <li><tt>work</tt>: The contact information may be used to contact in a professional context.</li>
          </ul>
        </section>
        <section anchor="prop-label" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>label</name>
          <t>Type: <tt>String</tt></t>
          <t>This property allows associating contact data with user-defined labels.  Such labels may be set for phone numbers, email addresses and resources.  Typically, these labels are displayed along with their associated contact data in graphical user interfaces.  Such labels best be succinct to properly display on small graphical interfaces and screens.</t>
        </section>
        <section anchor="prop-pref" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>pref</name>
          <t>Type: <tt>UnsignedInt</tt></t>
          <t>This property allows defining a preference order for contact information.  For example, a person may have two email addresses and prefer to be contacted with one of them.</t>
          <t>Its value <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be in the range 1 and 100.  Lower values correspond to a higher level of preference, with 1 being most preferred.  If no preference is set, then the contact information <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be interpreted as being least preferred.</t>
          <t>Note that the preference only is defined in relation to contact information of the same type.  For example, the preference orders within emails and phone numbers are independent of each other.</t>
        </section>
        <section anchor="prop-phonetic" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>phonetic</name>
          <t>This property defines how to pronounce a value in the language indicated in the Card <xref target="language">language</xref> property or the language tag of its <xref target="localizations">localizations</xref>.  Exemplary uses are to define how to pronounce Japanese names, or for romanization of Mandarin or Cantonese name and address components.  The properties are defined as follows:</t>
          <ul spacing="normal">
            <li>
              <t>phonetic: <tt>String</tt>.
                Contains the phonetic representation of a value.  Any script language subtag in the Card <xref target="language">language</xref> property <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be ignored for use with the <tt>phonetic</tt> property.  If this property is set, then at least one of the <tt>phoneticScript</tt> or <tt>phoneticSystem</tt> properties that relate to this value <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be set.</t>
            </li>
            <li>
              <t>phoneticScript: <tt>String</tt>.
                The script used in the value of the related <tt>phonetic</tt> property.  This <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be a valid script subtag as defined in <xref target="RFC5646" section="2.2.3"/>.</t>
            </li>
            <li>
              <t>phoneticSystem: <tt>String</tt>.
              The phonetic system used in the related value of the <tt>phonetic</tt> property.  The <xref target="enumerated-values">enumerated values</xref> are:</t>
              <ul>
                <li><tt>ipa</tt>: denotes the <xref target="IPA">International Phonetic Alphabet</xref>.</li>
                <li><tt>jyut</tt>: denotes the Cantonese romanization system "Jyutping".</li>
                <li><tt>piny</tt>: denotes the Standard Mandarin romanization system "Hanyu Pinyin".</li>
              </ul>
            </li>
          </ul>
          <t>The relation between the <tt>phoneticSystem</tt>, <tt>phoneticScript</tt> and <tt>phonetic</tt> properties is type-specific.  This specification defines this relation in the <xref target="name">Name</xref> and <xref target="addresses">Address</xref> object types, respectively.</t>
          <t>The following example illustrates the <tt>phonetic</tt> property for a <xref target="name">name</xref>:</t>
          <figure anchor="example-phonetic">
            <name>Example of <tt>phonetic</tt> for the name "John Smith" as pronounced in the USA.</name>
            <sourcecode name="" type="json"><![CDATA[
"name": {
  "components": [{
    "kind": "given",
    "value": "John",
    "phonetic": "/ˈdʒɑːn/"
  }, {
    "kind": "surname",
    "value": "Smith",
    "phonetic": "/smɪθ/"
  }],
  "phoneticSystem": "ipa"
}
]]></sourcecode>
          </figure>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section anchor="versioning">
        <name>Versioning</name>
        <t>Every instance of a JSContact <xref target="card">Card</xref> indicates which JSContact version its IANA-registered properties and values are based on.  The version is indicated both in the <xref target="prop-version"><tt>version</tt></xref> property within the Card and in the <xref target="iana-media-type">version</xref> parameter of the JSContact MIME content type. All IANA-registered elements indicate the version at which they got introduced or obsoleted.</t>
        <section>
          <name>Version Format and Requirements</name>
          <t>A JSContact version consists of a numeric major and minor version, separated by the <tt>FULL STOP</tt> character (U+002E).  Later versions are numerically higher than former versions, with the major version being more significant than the minor version. A version value is produced by the ABNF</t>
          <sourcecode name="" type="abnf"><![CDATA[
jsversion = 1*DIGIT "." 1*DIGIT
]]></sourcecode>
          <t>Differing major version values indicate substantial differences in JSContact semantics and format.  Implementations <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be prepared that property definitions and other JSContact elements differ in a backwards-incompatible manner.</t>
          <t>Differing minor version values indicate additions that enrich JSContact data, but do not introduce backwards-incompatible changes.  Typically, these are new property enum values or properties with narrow semantic scope.  A new minor version <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> require implementations to change their processing of JSContact data.  Changing the major version number resets the minor version number to zero.</t>
        </section>
        <section anchor="current-version">
          <name>Current Version</name>
          <t>This specification registers JSContact version value <tt>1.0</tt> (<xref target="tab-iana-version-registry"/>).</t>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section anchor="validating-jscontact">
        <name>Validating JSContact</name>
        <t>This specification distinguishes between three kinds of properties regarding validation: IANA-registered properties and unknown properties are defined in this section, while vendor-specific properties are defined in <xref target="vendor-specific-properties"/>.  A JSContact object is invalid if any of its properties are invalid.</t>
        <t>This document defines for each property if it is mandatory or optional.  A mandatory property <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be present for a JSContact object to be valid.  An optional property does not need to be present.  The values of both required and optional properties <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> adhere to the data type and definition of that property.</t>
        <section anchor="iana-registered-properties" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>IANA-registered Properties</name>
          <t>
         An IANA-registered property is any property that has been registered according to the IANA property registry rules as outlined in <xref target="iana-considerations"/>.  All properties defined in this specification, including their object value types and enumerated values, are registered at IANA.
      </t>
          <t>
        Implementations <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> validate IANA-registered properties in JSContact data, unless they are unknown to the implementation (see <xref target="unknown-properties"/>).  They <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> reject invalid IANA-registered properties.  A property is invalid if its name matches the name of an IANA-registered property but the value violates its definition according to the JSContact specification version defined in the Card <tt>version</tt> property (<xref target="prop-version"/>).
      </t>
          <t>
            IANA-registered property names <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> contain US-ASCII control characters (U+0000 to U+001F, U+007F), the <tt>COLON</tt> (U+003A) or <tt>QUOTATION MARK</tt> (U+0022) characters.  They <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> only contain US-ASCII alphanumeric characters that match the ALPHA and DIGIT rules defined in <xref target="RFC5234" section="B.1"/>) or the <tt>COMMERCIAL AT</tt> (U+0040) character.  IANA-registered property names <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be notated in lower camel case.
</t>
        </section>
        <section anchor="unknown-properties" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>Unknown Properties</name>
          <t>
          Implementations may encounter JSContact data where a property name is unknown to that implementation, but the name adheres to the syntactic restrictions of IANA-registered property names.
          Implementations <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> treat such properties as invalid.  Instead, they <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> preserve them in the JSContact object.  Implementations that create or update JSContact data <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> only set IANA-registered properties or vendor-specific properties.  Preserving properties that are unknown to the implementation, is to allow applications and services to interoperate without data loss, even if not all of them implement the same set of JSContact extensions.
    </t>
        </section>
        <section anchor="enumerated-values" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>Enumerated Values</name>
          <t>Several properties  in this document restrict their allowed values to be from a list of String values.  These values are case-sensitive.  If not noted otherwise for a specific property, the initial list of values for such properties is registered at IANA in the <xref target="iana-enum-registry">JSContact Enum Values Registry</xref>.  Implementations <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> only set IANA-registered or <xref target="vendor-specific-values">vendor-specific</xref> values for such properties.</t>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section anchor="vendor-specific-extensions">
        <name>Vendor-Specific Extensions</name>
        <t>Vendors may extend properties and values for experimentation or to store contacts data that only is useful for a single service or application.  Such extensions are not meant for interoperation.  If instead interoperation is desired, vendors are strongly encouraged to define and register new properties, types and values at IANA.  <xref target="iana-considerations"/> defines how to register new properties, types or values at IANA.  <xref target="iana-registered-properties"/> defines the naming conventions for IANA-registered elements.</t>
        <section anchor="vendor-specific-properties" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>Vendor-specific Properties</name>
          <t>
            Vendor-specific property names <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> start with a vendor-specific prefix followed by a name, as produced by the <tt>v-extension</tt> ABNF below.  The vendor-specific prefix <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be a domain name under control of the service or application that sets the property, but it need not resolve in the Domain Name System <xref target="RFC1034"/> and <xref target="RFC1035"/>.  The prefix <tt>ietf.org</tt> and its subdomain names are reserved for IETF specifications.  The name <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> contain the <tt>TILDE</tt> (U+007E) and <tt>SOLIDUS</tt> (U+002F) characters, as these require special-escaping when encoding a JSON Pointer <xref target="RFC6901"/> for that property.
      </t>
          <t>
        Vendor-specific properties <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> be set in any JSContact object.  Implementations <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> preserve vendor-specific properties in JSContact data, irrespective if they know their use.  They <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> reject the property value as invalid, unless they are in control of the vendor-specific property as outlined in the above paragraph.
      </t>
          <t>The ABNF rule <tt>v-extension</tt> formally defines valid vendor-specific property names.  Note that the vendor prefix allows for more values than are allowed as Internationalized Domain Names (IDN) <xref target="RFC8499"/>.  This is to allow JSContact implementations simply validate property names without implementing the full set of rules that apply to domain names.</t>
          <figure anchor="vendor-property-abnf">
            <name>ABNF rules for vendor-specific property names</name>
            <sourcecode name="" type="abnf"><![CDATA[
v-extension = v-prefix ":" v-name

v-prefix = v-label *("." v-label)

v-label = alnum-int / alnum-int *(alnum-int / "-") alnum-int

alnum-int = ALPHA / DIGIT / NON-ASCII
  ; see RFC 6350 Section 3.3

v-name = 1*(WSP / "!" / %x23-2e / %x30-7d / NON-ASCII)
  ; any characters except CTLs, DQUOTE, SOLIDUS and TILDE
]]></sourcecode>
          </figure>
          <t>
            The value of vendor-specific properties can be any valid JSON value, and naming restrictions do not apply to such values.  Specifically, if the property value is a JSON object then the keys of such objects need not be named as vendor-specific properties.  The example in <xref target="vendor-property-example"/> illustrates this:
      </t>
          <figure anchor="vendor-property-example">
            <name>Examples of vendor-specific properties</name>
            <artwork><![CDATA[
"example.com:foo": "bar",
"example.com:foo2": {
  "bar": "baz"
}
]]></artwork>
          </figure>
        </section>
        <section anchor="vendor-specific-values" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>Vendor-specific Values</name>
          <t>
            Some JSContact IANA-registered properties allow their values to be vendor-specific.  One such example is the <tt>kind</tt> property <xref target="kind"/>, which enumerates its standard values but also allows for arbitrary vendor-specific values.  Such vendor-specific values <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be valid <tt>v-extension</tt> values as defined in <xref target="vendor-specific-properties"/>.  The example in <xref target="vendor-value-example"/> illustrates this:
      </t>
          <figure anchor="vendor-value-example">
            <name>Example of a vendor-specific value</name>
            <artwork><![CDATA[
"kind": "example.com:baz"
]]></artwork>
          </figure>
          <t>
      Vendors are strongly encouraged to specify a new standard value once a vendor-specific one turns out to be useful also for other systems.
      </t>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section anchor="reserved-prop-names">
        <name>Reserved Property Names</name>
        <t>This specification reserves the property name <tt>extra</tt> at IANA.  Its sole purpose is to provide implementors with an internal variable name which is certain to never occur as a property name in a JSContact object.  Implementations might want to map unknown or vendor-specific properties to a variable with this name, but this is implementation-specific.  Any JSContact object including a property with this name is invalid.</t>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section anchor="card" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Card</name>
      <t>This section defines the JSContact object type Card. A Card stores contact information, typically that of a person, organization or company.</t>
      <t>Its media type is defined in <xref target="iana-media-type"/>.</t>
      <t><xref target="example-card"/>  basic Card for the person "John Doe".  As the object is the topmost object in the JSON data it has the <tt>@type</tt> property set according to the rules defined <xref target="prop-type"/>.</t>
      <figure anchor="example-card">
        <name>Example of a basic <tt>Card</tt></name>
        <sourcecode name="" type="json"><![CDATA[
{
  "@type": "Card",
  "version": "1.0",
  "uid": "22B2C7DF-9120-4969-8460-05956FE6B065",
  "kind": "individual",
  "name": {
    "components": [
      { "kind": "given", "value": "John" },
      { "kind": "surname", "value": "Doe" }
    ],
    "isOrdered": true
  }
}
]]></sourcecode>
      </figure>
      <section anchor="metadata-properties" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Metadata Properties</name>
        <t>This section defines properties about this instance of a Card, such as its unique identifier, its creation date, how it relates to other Cards and other metadata information.</t>
        <section anchor="cardtype" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>@type</name>
          <t>Type: <tt>String</tt> (mandatory).</t>
          <t>This <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be <tt>Card</tt>, if set.</t>
        </section>
        <section anchor="prop-version" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>version</name>
          <t>Type: <tt>String</tt> (mandatory).</t>
          <t>Specifies the JSContact version used to define this Card.  The value <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be one of the IANA-registered JSContact Enum Values for the <tt>version</tt> property.  Also see <xref target="current-version"/>.</t>
          <figure anchor="example-version">
            <name><tt>version</tt> example</name>
            <sourcecode name="" type="json"><![CDATA[
"version": "1.0"
]]></sourcecode>
          </figure>
        </section>
        <section anchor="created" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>created</name>
          <t>Type: <tt>UTCDateTime</tt> (optional).</t>
          <t>The date and time when this Card was created.</t>
          <figure anchor="example-created">
            <name><tt>created</tt> example</name>
            <sourcecode name="" type="json"><![CDATA[
"created": "2022-09-30T14:35:10Z",
]]></sourcecode>
          </figure>
        </section>
        <section anchor="kind" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>kind</name>
          <t>Type: <tt>String</tt> (optional).  The kind of the entity the Card represents.</t>
          <t>The <xref target="enumerated-values">enumerated</xref> values are:</t>
          <ul spacing="normal">
            <li><tt>individual</tt>: a single person</li>
            <li><tt>group</tt>: a group person of persons or entities</li>
            <li><tt>org</tt>: an organization</li>
            <li><tt>location</tt>: a named location</li>
            <li><tt>device</tt>: a device, such as appliances, computers, or network elements</li>
            <li><tt>application</tt>: a software application</li>
          </ul>
          <figure anchor="example-kind">
            <name><tt>kind</tt> example</name>
            <sourcecode name="" type="json"><![CDATA[
"kind": "individual",
]]></sourcecode>
          </figure>
        </section>
        <section anchor="language" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>language</name>
          <t>Type: <tt>String</tt> (optional).</t>
          <t>This is the language tag, as defined in <xref target="RFC5646"/>, that best describes the language used for text in the Card, optionally including additional information such as the script.  Note that values <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> be localized in the <tt>localizations</tt> property <xref target="localizations"/>.  How to render text is out of scope of this specification, e.g., refer to <xref target="UBiDi"/> how to deal with different writing directions.</t>
          <figure anchor="example-language">
            <name><tt>language</tt> example</name>
            <sourcecode name="" type="json"><![CDATA[
"language": "de-AT",
]]></sourcecode>
          </figure>
        </section>
        <section anchor="members" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>members</name>
          <t>Type: <tt>String[Boolean]</tt> (optional).</t>
          <t>This identifies the set of Cards that are members of this group Card.  Each key in the set is the <tt>uid</tt> property value of the member, each boolean value <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be <tt>true</tt>. If this property is set, then the value of the <tt>kind</tt> property <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be <tt>group</tt>.</t>
          <t>The opposite is not true.  A group Card will usually contain the <tt>members</tt> property to specify the members of the group, but it is not required to.  A group Card without the <tt>members</tt> property can be considered an abstract grouping, or one whose members are known empirically (e.g.,  "IETF Participants").</t>
          <figure anchor="example-members">
            <name><tt>members</tt> example</name>
            <sourcecode name="" type="json"><![CDATA[
"kind": "group",
"name": {
  "full": "The Doe family"
},
"uid": "urn:uuid:ab4310aa-fa43-11e9-8f0b-362b9e155667",
"members": {
  "urn:uuid:03a0e51f-d1aa-4385-8a53-e29025acd8af": true,
  "urn:uuid:b8767877-b4a1-4c70-9acc-505d3819e519": true
}
]]></sourcecode>
          </figure>
        </section>
        <section anchor="prodId" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>prodId</name>
          <t>Type: <tt>String</tt> (optional).</t>
          <t>The identifier for the product that created the Card.  If set, the value <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be at least one character long.</t>
          <figure anchor="example-prodId">
            <name><tt>prodId</tt> example</name>
            <sourcecode name="" type="json"><![CDATA[
"prodId": "ACME Contacts App version 1.23.5"
]]></sourcecode>
          </figure>
        </section>
        <section anchor="relatedTo" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>relatedTo</name>
          <t>Type: <tt>String[Relation]</tt> (optional).</t>
          <t>Relates the object to other Cards.  This is represented as a map, where each key is the <tt>uid</tt> of the related Card and the value defines the relation.  The Relation object has the following properties:</t>
          <ul spacing="normal">
            <li>@type: <tt>String</tt>.
            This <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be <tt>Relation</tt>, if set.
         </li>
            <li>
              <t>relation: <tt>String[Boolean]</tt> (optional, default: empty Object)
           Describes how the linked object is related to the linking object.  The relation is defined as a set of relation types.  The key in the set defines the relation type, the value for each key in the set <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be true.  The relationship between the two objects is undefined if the set is empty.</t>
              <t>The initial list of <xref target="enumerated-values">enumerated</xref> relation types matches the IANA-registered <xref target="IANAvCard">TYPE parameter</xref> values of the vCard RELATED property (<xref target="RFC6350" section="6.6.6"/>):</t>
              <ul>
                <li>
                  <tt>acquaintance</tt>
                </li>
                <li>
                  <tt>agent</tt>
                </li>
                <li>
                  <tt>child</tt>
                </li>
                <li>
                  <tt>colleague</tt>
                </li>
                <li>
                  <tt>contact</tt>
                </li>
                <li>
                  <tt>co-resident</tt>
                </li>
                <li>
                  <tt>co-worker</tt>
                </li>
                <li>
                  <tt>crush</tt>
                </li>
                <li>
                  <tt>date</tt>
                </li>
                <li>
                  <tt>emergency</tt>
                </li>
                <li>
                  <tt>friend</tt>
                </li>
                <li>
                  <tt>kin</tt>
                </li>
                <li>
                  <tt>me</tt>
                </li>
                <li>
                  <tt>met</tt>
                </li>
                <li>
                  <tt>muse</tt>
                </li>
                <li>
                  <tt>neighbor</tt>
                </li>
                <li>
                  <tt>parent</tt>
                </li>
                <li>
                  <tt>sibling</tt>
                </li>
                <li>
                  <tt>spouse</tt>
                </li>
                <li>
                  <tt>sweetheart</tt>
                </li>
              </ul>
            </li>
          </ul>
          <figure anchor="example-relatedto">
            <name><tt>relatedTo</tt> example</name>
            <sourcecode name="" type="json"><![CDATA[
"relatedTo": {
  "urn:uuid:f81d4fae-7dec-11d0-a765-00a0c91e6bf6": {
    "relation": {
      "friend": true
    }
  },
  "8cacdfb7d1ffdb59@example.com": {
    "relation": {}
  }
}
]]></sourcecode>
          </figure>
        </section>
        <section anchor="uid" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>uid</name>
          <t>Type: <tt>String</tt> (mandatory).</t>
          <t>An identifier, used to associate the object as the same across different systems, address books and views.  The value <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> be a URN <xref target="RFC8141"/> but for compatibility with <xref target="RFC6350"/> it <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> also be a URI <xref target="RFC3986"/> or free-text value.  The value of the URN <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> be in the <tt>uuid</tt> namespace <xref target="RFC4122" format="default"/>.  As of this writing, a <xref target="I-D.ietf-uuidrev-rfc4122bis">revision</xref> of the UUID standard document is being worked on and is likely to introduce new UUID versions and best practices to generate global unique identifiers.  Implementors <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> follow any recommendations described there.  Until then, implementations <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> generate identifiers using the random or pseudo-random UUID version described in <xref target="RFC4122" section="4.4"/>.</t>
          <figure anchor="example-uid">
            <name><tt>uid</tt> example</name>
            <sourcecode name="" type="json"><![CDATA[
"uid": "urn:uuid:f81d4fae-7dec-11d0-a765-00a0c91e6bf6"
]]></sourcecode>
          </figure>
        </section>
        <section anchor="updated" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>updated</name>
          <t>Type: <tt>UTCDateTime</tt> (optional).</t>
          <t>The date and time when the data in this Card was last modified.</t>
          <figure anchor="example-updated">
            <name><tt>updated</tt> example</name>
            <sourcecode name="" type="json"><![CDATA[
"updated": "2021-10-31T22:27:10Z"
]]></sourcecode>
          </figure>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section anchor="name-and-organization-properties" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Name and Organization Properties</name>
        <t>This section defines properties that name the entity represented by this Card, its related organizations and roles, as well as how to refer the entity represented by this Card in spoken or written language.</t>
        <section anchor="name" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>name</name>
          <t>Type: <tt>Name</tt> (optional).</t>
          <t>The name of the entity represented by this Card.  This can be any type of name, e.g., it can but need not be the legal name of a person.</t>
          <section>
            <name>Name object</name>
            <t>A Name object has the following properties</t>
            <ul spacing="normal">
              <li>@type: <tt>String</tt>.
              This <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be <tt>Name</tt>, if set.
          </li>
              <li>
                <t>components: <tt>NameComponent[]</tt> (optional).  The <xref target="namecomponent">components</xref> making up the name.  The component list <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> have at least one entry.  This property <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> be set, and it <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be set if the <tt>full</tt> property is not set.</t>
                <t>Name components <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> be ordered such that their values joined as a String produce a valid full name of this entity.  If so, implementations <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> set the <tt>isOrdered</tt> property value to "true".</t>
                <t>If the name components are ordered, then the <tt>defaultSeparator</tt> property and name components of kind <tt>separator</tt> give guidance what characters to insert between components, but implementations are free to choose any others.  In lack of a separator, inserting a single Space character in between name component values is a good choice.</t>
                <t>If instead the name components follow no particular order, then the <tt>isOrdered</tt> property value <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be "false", the <tt>components</tt> property <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> contain a NameComponent of kind <tt>separator</tt> and the <tt>defaultSeparator</tt> property <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> be set.</t>
                <t><xref target="example-name-twoword"/> is an example for the name "Vincent van Gogh".  Note how a single name component value may consist of multiple words.  <xref target="example-name-surname2"/> illustrates a name with a second surname, such as a Spanish name.  Additional examples are shown in <xref target="example-name-sortas"/> and <xref target="example-localizations-replace"/>.</t>
                <figure anchor="example-name-twoword">
                  <name>Example for a surname with two words</name>
                  <sourcecode name="" type="json"><![CDATA[
"name": {
  "components": [
    { "kind": "given", "value": "Vincent" },
    { "kind": "surname", "value": "van Gogh" }
  ],
  "isOrdered": true
}
]]></sourcecode>
                </figure>
                <figure anchor="example-name-surname2">
                  <name>Example for a second surname</name>
                  <sourcecode name="" type="json"><![CDATA[
"name": {
  "components": [
    { "kind": "given", "value": "Diego" },
    { "kind": "surname", "value": "Rivera" },
    { "kind": "surname2", "value": "Barrientos" }
  ],
  "isOrdered": true
}
]]></sourcecode>
                </figure>
              </li>
              <li>isOrdered: <tt>Boolean</tt> (optional, default: <tt>false</tt>).  This indicates if the name component sequence in the <tt>components</tt> property is ordered.</li>
              <li>defaultSeparator: <tt>String</tt> (optional).
                The default separator to insert between name component values when concatenating all name component values to a single String.  Also see the definition of the <tt>separator</tt> kind for the NameComponent object.  This property <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> be set if the Name <tt>isOrdered</tt> property value is <tt>false</tt> or if the <tt>components</tt> property is not set.</li>
              <li>
                <t>full: <tt>String</tt> (optional).
            This is the full name representation of this Name.  This property <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be set if the <tt>components</tt> property is not set.</t>
                <figure anchor="example-full">
                  <name><tt>full</tt> example</name>
                  <sourcecode name="" type="json"><![CDATA[
"full": "Mr. John Q. Public, Esq."
]]></sourcecode>
                </figure>
              </li>
              <li>
                <t>sortAs: <tt>String[String]</tt> (optional).</t>
                <t>This defines how this name lexicographically sorts in relation to other names when compared by a name component type.  The key in the map defines the name component type.  The value for that key defines the verbatim string to compare when sorting by this name component type.  Absence of a key indicates that this name component type should not be considered during sort.  Sorting by that missing name component type or if the <tt>sortAs</tt> property is not set is implementation-specific.  This property <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> be set if the <tt>components</tt> property is not set.</t>
                <t>Each key in the map <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be a valid name component type value as defined for the <tt>kind</tt> property of the NameComponent object (see below).  For each key in the map there <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> exist at least one NameComponent object having that type in the <tt>components</tt> property of this name.</t>
                <t><xref target="example-name-sortas"/> illustrates the use of sortAs.  The property value indicates that the middle name followed by both surnames should be used when sorting this name by surname.  The absence of the <tt>middle</tt> indicates that the middle name on its own should be disregarded during sort.  Even though the name only contains one name component for the given name, the sortAs property still explicitly defines how to sort by given name as otherwise sorting by it would be undefined.</t>
              </li>
              <li>
                <t>phoneticScript: <tt>String</tt> (optional).
                The script used in the value of the NameComponent <tt>phonetic</tt> property.  Also see <xref target="prop-phonetic"/>.  See <xref target="example-name-phonetic"/> for an example.</t>
              </li>
              <li>
                <t>phoneticSystem: <tt>String</tt> (optional).
              The phonetic system used in the NameComponent <tt>phonetic</tt> property.  Also      see <xref target="prop-phonetic"/>.  See <xref target="example-name-phonetic"/> for an example.</t>
              </li>
            </ul>

                <figure anchor="example-name-sortas">
                  <name>Example for <tt>sortAs</tt></name>
                  <sourcecode name="" type="json"><![CDATA[
"name": {
  "components": [
    { "kind": "given", "value": "Robert" },
    { "kind": "given2", "value": "Pau" },
    { "kind": "surname", "value": "Shou Chang" }
  ],
  "sortAs": {
    "surname": "Pau Shou Chang",
    "given": "Robert"
  },
  "isOrdered": "true"
}
]]></sourcecode>
                </figure>

          <figure anchor="example-name-phonetic">
            <name>Example for <tt>phonetic</tt> and <tt>localizations</tt></name>
            <artwork><![CDATA[
{
  "@type": "Card",
  "language": "zh-Hant",
  "name": {
    "components": [
      { "kind": "surname", "value": "孫" },
      { "kind": "given", "value": "中山" },
      { "kind": "given2", "value": "文" },
      { "kind": "given2", "value": "逸仙" }
    ]
  },
  "localizations": {
    "yue": {
      "name/phoneticSystem": "jyut",
      "name/phoneticScript": "Latn",
      "name/components/0/phonetic": "syun1",
      "name/components/1/phonetic": "zung1saan1",
      "name/components/2/phonetic": "man4",
      "name/components/3/phonetic": "jat6sin1"
    }
  }
}
]]></artwork>
          </figure>
          </section>
          <section anchor="namecomponent">
            <name>NameComponent</name>
            <t>A NameComponent object has the following properties:</t>
            <ul spacing="normal">
              <li>@type: <tt>String</tt>.
              This <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be <tt>NameComponent</tt>, if set.
          </li>
              <li>value: <tt>String</tt> (mandatory).
The value of this name component.  This can be composed of one or multiple words, such as "Poe" or "van Gogh".</li>
              <li>
                <t>kind: <tt>String</tt> (mandatory).
              The kind of this name component.  The <xref target="enumerated-values">enumerated</xref> values are:
</t>
                <ul spacing="normal">
                  <li><tt>title</tt>.  The value is an honorific title or prefix, e.g.,  "Mr", "Ms", "Dr".</li>
                  <li><tt>given</tt>.  The value is a given name, also known as "first name", "personal name".</li>
                  <li><tt>given2</tt>.  The value is a name that appears between the given and surname, such as a middle name or patronymic name</li>
                  <li><tt>surname</tt>.  The value is a surname, also known as "last name", "family name".</li>
                  <li><tt>surname2</tt>.  The value is a secondary surname (used in some cultures), also known as "maternal surname".</li>
                  <li><tt>credential</tt>.  The value is a  credential, also known as "accreditation qualifier" or "honorific suffix", e.g.,  "B.A.", "Esq.".</li>
                  <li><tt>generation</tt>.  The value is a generation marker or qualifier, e.g.,  “Jr.” or “III”.</li>
                  <li><tt>separator</tt>.  A formatting separator between two ordered name non-separator components.  The <tt>value</tt> property of the component includes the verbatim separator, for example a hyphen character or even an empty string.  This value has higher precedence than the <tt>defaultSeparator</tt> property of the Name.  Implementations <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> insert two consecutive separator components, instead they <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> insert a single separator component with the combined value.  This component kind <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> be set if the Name <tt>isOrdered</tt> property value is <tt>false</tt>.</li>
                </ul>
              </li>
              <li>phonetic: <tt>String</tt> (optional).  This defines how to pronounce this name component.  If this property is set, then at least one of the Name object <tt>phoneticSystem</tt> or <tt>phoneticScript</tt> properties <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be set.  Also see <xref target="prop-phonetic"/>.</li>
            </ul>
          </section>
          <section anchor="nicknames" numbered="true" toc="default">
            <name>nicknames</name>
            <t>Type: <tt>Id[Nickname]</tt> (optional).</t>
            <t>The nicknames of the entity represented by this Card.  A Nickname object has the following properties:</t>
            <ul spacing="normal">
              <li>@type: <tt>String</tt>.
              This <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be <tt>Nickname</tt>, if set.
          </li>
              <li>name: <tt>String</tt> (mandatory).
            The nickname.
        </li>
              <li>contexts: <tt>String[Boolean]</tt> (optional)
The contexts in which to use this nickname.  Also see <xref target="prop-contexts"/>.</li>
              <li>pref: <tt>UnsignedInt</tt> (optional).
            The preference of this nickname in relation to other nicknames.  Also see <xref target="prop-pref"/>.</li>
            </ul>
            <figure anchor="example-nicknames">
              <name><tt>nicknames</tt> example</name>
              <sourcecode name="" type="json"><![CDATA[
"nicknames": {
  "k391": {
    "name": "Johnny"
  }
}
]]></sourcecode>
            </figure>
          </section>
        </section>
        <section anchor="organizations" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>organizations</name>
          <t>Type: <tt>Id[Organization]</tt> (optional).</t>
          <t>The companies or organization names and units associated with this Card.  An Organization object has the following properties, of which at least one of the <tt>name</tt> and <tt>units</tt> properties <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be set:</t>
          <ul spacing="normal">
            <li>@type: <tt>String</tt>.
              This <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be <tt>Organization</tt>, if set.
          </li>
            <li>name: <tt>String</tt> (optional).
            The name of this organization.
        </li>
            <li>units: <tt>OrgUnit[]</tt> (optional).
            A list of organizational units, ordered descending by hierarchy (e.g., a geographic or functional division sorts before a department within that division).  If set, the list <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> contain at least one entry.
        </li>
            <li>sortAs: <tt>String</tt> (optional).
            This defines how this organization name lexicographically sorts in relation to other organizations when compared by name.  The value defines the verbatim string value to compare.  In absence of this property, the <tt>name</tt> property value <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> be used for comparison.
        </li>
            <li>contexts: <tt>String[Boolean]</tt> (optional).
The contexts in which association with this organization apply.  For example, membership in a choir may only apply in a private context.  Also see <xref target="prop-contexts"/>.</li>
          </ul>
          <t>A OrgUnit object has the following properties:</t>
          <ul spacing="normal">
            <li>@type: <tt>String</tt>.
              This <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be <tt>OrgUnit</tt>, if set.
          </li>
            <li>name: <tt>String</tt> (mandatory).
            The name of this organizational unit.
        </li>
            <li>sortAs: <tt>String</tt> (optional).
            This defines how this organization unit name lexicographically sorts in relation to other organizational units of the same level when compared by name.  The level is defined by the array index of this organizational unit in the <tt>units</tt> property of the Organization object.  The property value defines the verbatim string value to compare.  In absence of this property, the <tt>name</tt> property value <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> be used for comparison.
        </li>
          </ul>
          <figure anchor="example-organizations">
            <name><tt>organizations</tt> example</name>
            <sourcecode name="" type="json"><![CDATA[
"organizations": {
  "o1": {
    "name": "ABC, Inc.",
    "units": [
      { "name": "North American Division" },
      { "name": "Marketing" }
    ],
    "sortAs": "ABC"
  }
}
]]></sourcecode>
          </figure>
        </section>
        <section anchor="speakToAs" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>speakToAs</name>
          <t>Type: <tt>SpeakToAs</tt> (optional).</t>
          <t>Provides information how to address, speak to or refer to the entity that is represented by this Card.  A SpeakToAs object has the following properties, of which at least one of the <tt>grammaticalGender</tt> and <tt>pronouns</tt> properties <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be set:</t>
          <ul spacing="normal">
            <li>@type: <tt>String</tt>.
              This <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be <tt>SpeakToAs</tt>, if set.
          </li>
            <li>
              <t>grammaticalGender: <tt>String</tt> (optional).
              Defines which grammatical gender to use in salutations and other grammatical constructs.
              For example, the German language distinguishes by grammatical gender in salutations such as "Sehr geehrte" (feminine) and "Sehr geehrter" (masculine).
              The <xref target="enumerated-values">enumerated</xref> values are:</t>
              <ul spacing="normal">
                <li>
                  <tt>animate</tt>
                </li>
                <li>
                  <tt>common</tt>
                </li>
                <li>
                  <tt>feminine</tt>
                </li>
                <li>
                  <tt>inanimate</tt>
                </li>
                <li>
                  <tt>masculine</tt>
                </li>
                <li>
                  <tt>neuter</tt>
                </li>
              </ul>
              <t>Note that the grammatical gender does not allow inferring the gender identities or assigned sex of the contact.</t>
            </li>
            <li>
              <t>pronouns: <tt>Id[Pronouns]</tt> (optional).
             Defines the pronouns that the contact chooses to use for themselves.</t>
            </li>
          </ul>
          <t>A Pronouns object has the following properties:</t>
          <ul spacing="normal">
            <li>@type: <tt>String</tt>.
              This <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be <tt>Pronouns</tt>, if set.
          </li>
            <li>pronouns: <tt>String</tt> (mandatory).
              Defines the pronouns.  Any value or form is allowed.  Examples in English include <tt>she/her</tt> and <tt>they/them/theirs</tt>.  The value <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> be overridden in the <tt>localizations</tt> property (<xref target="localizations"/>).</li>
            <li>contexts: <tt>String[Boolean]</tt> (optional).
The contexts in which to use these pronouns.  Also see <xref target="prop-contexts"/>.</li>
            <li>pref: <tt>UnsignedInt</tt> (optional).
            The preference of these pronouns in relation to other pronouns in the same context.  Also see <xref target="prop-pref"/>.</li>
          </ul>
          <figure anchor="example-speakToAs">
            <name><tt>speakToAs</tt> example</name>
            <sourcecode name="" type="json"><![CDATA[
"speakToAs": {
  "grammaticalGender": "neuter",
  "pronouns": {
    "k19": {
      "pronouns": "they/them",
      "pref": 2
    },
    "k32": {
      "pronouns": "xe/xir",
      "pref": 1
    }
  }
}
]]></sourcecode>
          </figure>
        </section>
        <section anchor="titles" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>titles</name>
          <t>Type : <tt>Id[Title]</tt> (optional).</t>
          <t>The job titles or functional positions of the entity represented by this Card.  A Title object has the following properties:</t>
          <ul spacing="normal">
            <li>@type: <tt>String</tt>.
              This <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be <tt>Title</tt>, if set.
          </li>
            <li>name: <tt>String</tt> (mandatory).
            The title or role name of the entity represented by this Card.
        </li>
            <li>
              <t>kind: <tt>String</tt> (optional, default <tt>title</tt>).
          Describes the organizational or situational kind of this title.  Some organizations and individuals distinguish between <em>titles</em> as organizational positions and <em>roles</em> as more temporary assignments, such as in project management.</t>
              <t>The <xref target="enumerated-values">enumerated</xref> values are:</t>
              <ul>
                <li>
                  <tt>title</tt>
                </li>
                <li>
                  <tt>role</tt>
                </li>
              </ul>
            </li>
            <li>organization: <tt>Id</tt> (optional).
            The identifier of the organization in which this title is held.
        </li>
          </ul>
          <figure anchor="example-titles">
            <name><tt>titles</tt> example</name>
            <sourcecode name="" type="json"><![CDATA[
"titles": {
  "le9": {
    "kind": "title",
    "name": "Research Scientist"
  },
  "k2": {
    "kind": "role",
    "name": "Project Leader",
    "organization": "o2"
  }
},
"organizations": {
  "o2": {
    "name": "ABC, Inc."
  }
}
]]></sourcecode>
          </figure>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section anchor="contact-properties" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Contact Properties</name>
        <t>This section defines properties how to contact the entity represented by this Card.</t>
        <section anchor="emails" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>emails</name>
          <t>Type: <tt>Id[EmailAddress]</tt> (optional).</t>
          <t>The email addresses to contact the entity represented by this Card.  An EmailAddress object has the following properties:</t>
          <ul spacing="normal">
            <li>@type: <tt>String</tt>.
              This <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be <tt>EmailAddress</tt>, if set.
          </li>
            <li>address: <tt>String</tt> (mandatory).
The email address.  This <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be an <em>addr-spec</em> value as defined in Section 3.4.1 of <xref target="RFC5322" format="default"/>.</li>
            <li>contexts: <tt>String[Boolean]</tt> (optional).
The contexts in which to use this email address.  Also see <xref target="prop-contexts"/>.</li>
            <li>pref: <tt>UnsignedInt</tt> (optional).
            The preference of this email address in relation to other email addresses.  Also see <xref target="prop-pref"/>.</li>
            <li>label: <tt>String</tt> (optional).
            A custom label for the value, see <xref target="prop-label"/>.</li>
          </ul>
          <figure anchor="example-emails">
            <name><tt>emails</tt> example</name>
            <sourcecode name="" type="json"><![CDATA[
"emails": {
  "e1": {
    "contexts": {
      "work": true
    },
    "address": "jqpublic@xyz.example.com"
  },
  "e2": {
    "address": "jane_doe@example.com",
    "pref": 1
  }
}
]]></sourcecode>
          </figure>
        </section>
        <section anchor="onlineServices" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>onlineServices</name>
          <t>Type: <tt>Id[OnlineService]</tt> (optional).</t>
          <t>The online services that are associated with the entity represented by this Card.  This can be messaging services, social media profiles, and other.  An OnlineService object has the following properties, of which at least the <tt>uri</tt> or <tt>user</tt> property <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be set:</t>
          <ul spacing="normal">
            <li>@type: <tt>String</tt>.
              This <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be <tt>OnlineService</tt>, if set.
        </li>
            <li>service: <tt>String</tt> (optional).
              The name of the online service or protocol.  The name <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> be capitalized the same as on the service's website, app or publishing material, but names <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be considered equal is they match case-insensitively.  Examples are <tt>GitHub</tt>, <tt>kakao</tt>, <tt>Mastodon</tt>.</li>
            <li>uri: <tt>String</tt> (optional).
This identifies the entity represented by this card at the online service.  This <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be a <em>URI</em> as defined in Section 3 of <xref target="RFC3986" format="default"/> and updates.</li>
            <li>user: <tt>String</tt> (optional).
              This names the entity represented by this Card at the online service.  Any free-text value is allowed.  The <tt>service</tt> property <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> be set.</li>
            <li>contexts: <tt>String[Boolean]</tt> (optional).
The contexts in which to use this service.  Also see <xref target="prop-contexts"/>.</li>
            <li>pref: <tt>UnsignedInt</tt> (optional).
            The preference of this service in relation to other services.  Also see <xref target="prop-pref"/>.</li>
            <li>label: <tt>String</tt> (optional).
            A custom label for the value, see <xref target="prop-label"/>.</li>
          </ul>
          <figure anchor="example-onlineServices">
            <name><tt>onlineServices</tt> example</name>
            <sourcecode name="" type="json"><![CDATA[
"onlineServices": {
  "x1": {
    "uri": "xmpp:alice@example.com",
  },
  "x2": {
    "service": "Mastodon",
    "user": "@alice@example2.com",
    "uri": "https://example2.com/@alice",
  }
}
]]></sourcecode>
          </figure>
        </section>
        <section anchor="phones" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>phones</name>
          <t>Type: <tt>Id[Phone]</tt> (optional).</t>
          <t>The phone numbers to contact the entity represented by this Card.  A Phone object has the following properties:</t>
          <ul spacing="normal">
            <li>@type: <tt>String</tt>.
              This <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be <tt>Phone</tt>, if set.
          </li>
            <li>number: <tt>String</tt> (mandatory).
The phone number, as either a URI or free-text.  Typical URI schemes are the <xref target="RFC3966" format="default"/> <tt>tel</tt> or <xref target="RFC3261" format="default"/> <tt>sip</tt> schemes, but any URI scheme is allowed.</li>
            <li>
              <t>features: <tt>String[Boolean]</tt> (optional).
              The set of contact features that this phone number may be used for.  The set is represented as an object, with each key being a method type.  The boolean value <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be <tt>true</tt>.  The <xref target="enumerated-values">enumerated</xref> method type values are:
</t>
              <ul spacing="normal">
                <li><tt>mobile</tt> The number is for a mobile phone.</li>
                <li><tt>voice</tt> The number is for calling by voice.</li>
                <li><tt>text</tt> The number supports text messages (SMS).</li>
                <li><tt>video</tt> The number supports video conferencing.</li>
                <li><tt>main-number</tt> This number is the main phone number, such as the number of the front-desk at a company, as opposed to a direct-dial number of an individual employee.</li>
                <li><tt>textphone</tt> The number is for a device for people with hearing or speech difficulties.</li>
                <li><tt>fax</tt> The number is for sending faxes.</li>
                <li><tt>pager</tt> The number is for a pager or beeper.</li>
              </ul>
            </li>
            <li>contexts: <tt>String[Boolean]</tt> (optional).
The contexts in which to use this number.  Also see <xref target="prop-contexts"/>.</li>
            <li>pref: <tt>UnsignedInt</tt> (optional).
            The preference of this number in relation to other numbers.  Also see <xref target="prop-pref"/>.</li>
            <li>label: <tt>String</tt> (optional).
            A custom label for the value, see <xref target="prop-label"/>.</li>
          </ul>
          <figure anchor="example-phones">
            <name><tt>phones</tt> example</name>
            <sourcecode name="" type="json"><![CDATA[
"phones": {
  "tel0": {
    "contexts": {
      "private": true
    },
    "features": {
      "voice": true
    },
    "number": "tel:+1-555-555-5555;ext=5555",
    "pref": 1
  },
  "tel3": {
    "contexts": {
      "work": true
    },
    "number": "tel:+1-201-555-0123",
  }
}
]]></sourcecode>
          </figure>
        </section>
        <section anchor="preferredLanguages" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>preferredLanguages</name>
          <t>Type : <tt>Id[LanguagePref]</tt> (optional).</t>
          <t>Defines the preferred languages for contacting the entity associated with this Card.</t>
          <t>A LanguagePref object has the following properties:</t>
          <ul spacing="normal">
            <li>@type: <tt>String</tt>.
              This <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be <tt>LanguagePref</tt>, if set.
          </li>
            <li>language: <tt>String</tt> (mandatory).  The preferred language.  This <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> a language tag as defined in <xref target="RFC5646"/>.</li>
            <li>contexts: <tt>String[Boolean]</tt> (optional).
Defines the contexts in which to use this language.  Also see <xref target="prop-contexts"/>.</li>
            <li>pref: <tt>UnsignedInt</tt> (optional).
Defines the preference of this language in relation to other languages of the same contexts.  Also see <xref target="prop-pref"/>.</li>
          </ul>
          <figure anchor="example-preferredLanguages">
            <name><tt>preferredLanguages</tt> example</name>
            <sourcecode name="" type="json"><![CDATA[
"preferredLanguages": {
  "l1": {
    "language": "en",
    "contexts": {
      "work": true
    },
    "pref": 1
  },
  "l2": {
    "language": "fr",
    "contexts": {
      "work": true
    },
    "pref": 2
  },
  "l3": {
    "language": "fr",
    "contexts": {
      "private": true
    }
  }
}
]]></sourcecode>
          </figure>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section anchor="calendaring-and-scheduling-properties" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Calendaring and Scheduling Properties</name>
        <t>This section defines properties how to schedule calendar events with the entity represented by this Card.</t>
        <section anchor="calendars" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>calendars</name>
          <t>Type: <tt>Id[Calendar]</tt> (optional).</t>
          <t>These are resources for calendaring, such as calendars to lookup free-busy information for the entity represented by this Card.  A Calendar object has all properties of the <xref target="resource">Resource</xref> data type, with the following additional definitions:</t>
          <ul>
            <li>The <tt>@type</tt> property value <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be <tt>Calendar</tt>, if set.</li>
          </ul>
          <t>The <tt>kind</tt> property is mandatory.  Its <xref target="enumerated-values">enumerated</xref> values are:</t>
          <ul>
            <li><tt>calendar</tt> The resource is a calendar that contains entries such as calendar events or tasks.</li>
            <li><tt>freeBusy</tt> The resource allows for free-busy lookups, for example to schedule group events.</li>
          </ul>
          <figure anchor="example-calendars">
            <name><tt>calendars</tt> example</name>
            <sourcecode name="" type="json"><![CDATA[
"calendars": {
  "calA": {
    "kind": "calendar",
    "uri": "webcal://calendar.example.com/calA.ics"
  },
  "project-a": {
    "kind": "freeBusy",
    "uri": "https://calendar.example.com/busy/project-a"
  }
}
]]></sourcecode>
          </figure>
        </section>
        <section anchor="schedulingAddresses" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>schedulingAddresses</name>
          <t>Type: <tt>Id[SchedulingAddress]</tt> (optional).</t>
          <t>The scheduling addresses by which the entity may receive calendar scheduling invitations.  A SchedulingAddress object has the following properties:</t>
          <ul spacing="normal">
            <li>
              <t>@type: <tt>String</tt>.
              This <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be <tt>SchedulingAddress</tt>, if set.</t>
            </li>
            <li>uri: <tt>String</tt> (mandatory).
The address to use for calendar scheduling with this contact.  This <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be a URI as defined in Section 3 of <xref target="RFC3986" format="default"/> and updates.</li>
            <li>contexts: <tt>String[Boolean]</tt> (optional).
The contexts in which to use this scheduling address.  Also see <xref target="prop-contexts"/>.</li>
            <li>pref: <tt>UnsignedInt</tt> (optional).
            The preference of this scheduling address in relation to other scheduling address.  Also see <xref target="prop-pref"/>.</li>
            <li>label: <tt>String</tt> (optional).
            A custom label for the scheduling address, see <xref target="prop-label"/>.</li>
          </ul>
          <figure anchor="example-schedulingAddresses">
            <name><tt>schedulingAddresses</tt> example</name>
            <sourcecode name="" type="json"><![CDATA[
"schedulingAddresses": {
  "sched1": {
    "uri": "mailto:janedoe@example.com"
  }
}
]]></sourcecode>
          </figure>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section anchor="address-and-location-properties" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Address and Location Properties</name>
        <t>This section defines properties for postal addresses and geographical locations associated with the entity represented by this Card.</t>
        <section anchor="addresses" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>addresses</name>
          <t>Type: <tt>Id[Address]</tt> (optional).</t>
          <t>A map of address identifiers to Address objects, containing physical locations.</t>
          <section>
            <name>Address object</name>
            <t>An Address object has the following properties:</t>
            <ul spacing="normal">
              <li>@type: <tt>String</tt>.
              This <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be <tt>Address</tt>, if set.
          </li>
              <li>
                <t>components: <tt>AddressComponent[]</tt> (optional).
                The <xref target="addresscomponent">components</xref> making up this address.  The component list <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> have at least one entry.  This property <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> be set, and it <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be set if the <tt>full</tt> property is not set.</t>
                <t>Address components <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> be ordered such that their values joined as a String produce a valid full address.  If so, implementations <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> set the <tt>isOrdered</tt> property value to "true".</t>
                <t>If the address components are ordered, then the <tt>defaultSeparator</tt> property and address components of kind <tt>separator</tt> give guidance what characters to insert between components, but implementations are free to choose any others.  In lack of a separator, inserting a single Space character in between address component values is a good choice.</t>
                <t>If instead the address components follow no particular order, then the <tt>isOrdered</tt> property value <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be "false", the <tt>components</tt> property <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> contain a AddressComponent of kind <tt>separator</tt> and the <tt>defaultSeparator</tt> property <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> be set.</t>
              </li>
              <li>isOrdered: <tt>Boolean</tt> (optional, default: <tt>false</tt>).  This indicates if the address component sequence in the <tt>components</tt> property is ordered.</li>
              <li>countryCode: <tt>String</tt> (optional).
The Alpha-2 country code <xref target="ISO.3166-1.2006"/>.</li>
              <li>coordinates: <tt>String</tt> (optional).  A <xref target="RFC5870" format="default"/> "geo:" URI for the address.</li>
              <li>timeZone: <tt>String</tt> (optional).  Identifies the time zone this address is located in.  This <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be a time zone name registered in the <xref target="IANATZ">IANA Time Zone Database</xref></li>
              <li>
                <t>contexts: <tt>String[Boolean]</tt> (optional).
The contexts of the address information.  The boolean value <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be <tt>true</tt>.  In addition to the common contexts (<xref target="prop-contexts"/>), allowed key values are:
</t>
                <ul spacing="normal">
                  <li><tt>billing</tt> An address to be used for billing.</li>
                  <li><tt>delivery</tt> An address to be used for delivering physical items.</li>
                </ul>
              </li>
              <li>full: <tt>String</tt> (optional).
              This is the full address, including street, region or country.  The purpose of this property is to define an address, even if the individual address components are not known.  If the <tt>street</tt> property is set, the <tt>full</tt> property <bcp14>SHOULD NOT</bcp14> be set.
            </li>
              <li>defaultSeparator: <tt>String</tt> (optional).
              The default separator to insert between address component values when concatenating all address component values to a single String.  Also see the definition of the <tt>separator</tt> kind for the AddressComponent object.  This property <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> be set if the Address <tt>isOrdered</tt> property value is <tt>false</tt> or if the <tt>components</tt> property is not set.</li>
              <li>pref: <tt>UnsignedInt</tt> (optional).
            The preference of this address in relation to other addresses.  Also see <xref target="prop-pref"/>.</li>
              <li>
                <t>phoneticScript: <tt>String</tt> (optional).
                The script used in the value of the AddressComponent <tt>phonetic</tt> property.  Also see <xref target="prop-phonetic"/>.</t>
              </li>
              <li>
                <t>phoneticSystem: <tt>String</tt> (optional).
              The phonetic system used in the AddressComponent <tt>phonetic</tt> property.  Also      see <xref target="prop-phonetic"/>.</t>
              </li>
            </ul>
            <t>The following example illustrates the use of the <tt>address</tt> property.  Additional examples are in <xref target="address-examples"/>.</t>
            <figure anchor="example-address-us">
              <name>Example of the address "54321 Oak St, Reston, VA 20190, USA"</name>
              <sourcecode name="" type="json"><![CDATA[
"addresses": {
  "k23": {
    "contexts": {
      "work": true
    },
    "components": [
      { "kind": "number", "value": "54321" },
      { "kind": "separator", "value": " " },
      { "kind": "name", "value": "Oak St" },
      { "kind": "locality", "value": "Reston" },
      { "kind": "region", "value": "VA" },
      { "kind": "separator", "value": " " },
      { "kind": "postcode", "value": "20190" },
      { "kind": "country", "value": "USA" }
    ],
    "countryCode": "US",
    "defaultSeparator": ", ",
    "isOrdered": true
  }
}
]]></sourcecode>
            </figure>
          </section>
          <section anchor="addresscomponent">
            <name>AddressComponent object</name>
            <t>An AddressComponent object has the following properties:</t>
            <ul spacing="normal">
              <li>@type: <tt>String</tt>.
              This <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be <tt>AddressComponent</tt>, if set.
            </li>
              <li>value: <tt>String</tt> (mandatory).
The value of this address component.</li>
              <li>
                <t>kind: <tt>String</tt> (mandatory).
              The kind of this address component.  The <xref target="enumerated-values">enumerated</xref> values are:
</t>
                <ul spacing="normal">
                  <li><tt>room</tt>.  The room or suite number or identifier.</li>
                  <li><tt>apartment</tt>.  The extension designation, such as apartment number or unit or box number.</li>
                  <li><tt>floor</tt>.  The floor or level this address is located on.</li>
                  <li><tt>building</tt>.  The building, tower, or condominium this address is located in.</li>
                  <li><tt>number</tt>.  The street number, e.g., "123".  This value is not restricted to numeric values, and can include any value such as number ranges ("112–10"), grid style ("39.2 RD"), alphanumerics ("N6W23001") or fractionals ("123 1/2").</li>
                  <li><tt>name</tt>.  The street name.</li>
                  <li><tt>block</tt>. The block name or number.</li>
                  <li><tt>subdistrict</tt>. The sub district, ward or other subunit of a district.</li>
                  <li><tt>district</tt>. The district name.</li>
                  <li><tt>locality</tt>. The municipality, city, town, village, post-town, or another locality.</li>
                  <li><tt>region</tt>. The administrative area, such as province, state, prefecture, county, canton.</li>
                  <li><tt>postcode</tt>. The postal code, post code, ZIP code or other short code associated with the address by the relevant country's postal system.</li>
                  <li><tt>country</tt>. The country name.</li>
                  <li><tt>direction</tt>.  The Cardinal direction or quadrant, e.g.,  "North".</li>
                  <li><tt>landmark</tt>. The publicly known prominent feature that can substitute the street name and number, e.g., White House, Taj Mahal.</li>
                  <li><tt>postOfficeBox</tt>.  The post office box number or identifier.</li>
                  <li><tt>separator</tt>.  A formatting separator between two ordered address non-separator components.  The <tt>value</tt> property of the component includes the verbatim separator, for example a hyphen character or even an empty string.  This value has higher precedence than the <tt>defaultSeparator</tt> property of the Address.  Implementations <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> insert two consecutive separator components, instead they <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> insert a single separator component with the combined value.  This component kind <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> be set if the Address <tt>isOrdered</tt> property value is <tt>false</tt>.</li>
                </ul>
              </li>
              <li>phonetic: <tt>String</tt> (optional).  This defines how to pronounce this name component.  If this property is set, then at least one of the Address object <tt>phoneticSystem</tt> or <tt>phoneticScript</tt> properties <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be set.  Also see <xref target="prop-phonetic"/>.</li>
            </ul>
          </section>
          <section anchor="address-examples">
            <name>Address examples</name>
            <t>The following are examples of addresses, in addition to <xref target="example-address-us"/>.</t>
            <figure anchor="example-address-th">
              <name>Example of the address "46, 1 Sukhumvit 51 Alley, Khlong Tan Nuea, Watthana, Bangkok 10110, Thailand"</name>
              <sourcecode name="" type="json"><![CDATA[
"addresses": {
  "k25": {
    "components": [
      { "kind": "number", "value": "46" },
      { "kind": "name", "value": "1 Sukhumvit 51 Alley" },
      { "kind": "subdistrict", "value": "Khlong Tan Nuea" },
      { "kind": "district", "value": " Watthana" },
      { "kind": "locality", "value": "Bangkok" },
      { "kind": "country", "value": "Thailand" },
      { "kind": "postcode", "value": "10110" }
    ],
    "defaultSeparator": ", ",
    "isOrdered": true
  }
}
]]></sourcecode>
            </figure>
            <figure anchor="example-address-jp">
              <name>Example of an address in Tokyo and its localization <xref target="localizations"/> in Japanese.</name>
              <sourcecode name="" type="json"><![CDATA[
"addresses": {
   "k26": {
     "components": [
       { "kind": "block", "value": "2-7" },
       { "kind": "separator", "value": "-" },
       { "kind": "number", "value": "2" },
       { "kind": "separator", "value": " " },
       { "kind": "district", "value": "Marunouchi" },
       { "kind": "locality", "value": "Chiyoda-ku" },
       { "kind": "region", "value": "Tokyo" },
       { "kind": "separator", "value": " " },
       { "kind": "postcode", "value": "100-8994" }
     ],
     "defaultSeparator": ", ",
     "full": "2-7-2 Marunouchi, Chiyoda-ku, Tokyo 100-8994",
     "isOrdered": true
   }
},
"localizations": {
  "jp": {
    "addresses/k26": {
      "components": [
        { "kind": "region", "value": "東京都" },
        { "kind": "locality", "value": "千代田区" },
        { "kind": "district", "value": "丸ノ内" },
        { "kind": "block", "value": "2-7" },
        { "kind": "separator", "value": "-" },
        { "kind": "number", "value": "2" },
        { "kind": "postcode", "value": "〒100-8994" }
      ],
      "defaultSeparator": "",
      "full": "〒100-8994東京都千代田区丸ノ内2-7-2",
      "isOrdered": true
    }
  }
}
]]></sourcecode>
            </figure>
          </section>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section anchor="resource-properties" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Resource Properties</name>
        <t>This section defines properties for digital resources associated with the entity represented by this Card.</t>
        <section anchor="cryptoKeys" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>cryptoKeys</name>
          <t>Type: <tt>Id[CryptoKey]</tt> (optional).</t>
          <t>These are cryptographic resources such as public keys and certificates associated with the entity represented by this Card.  A CryptoKey object has all properties of the <xref target="resource">Resource</xref> data type, with the following additional definitions:</t>
          <ul>
            <li>The <tt>@type</tt> property value <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be <tt>CryptoKey</tt>, if set.</li>
          </ul>
          <t>The following example shows how refer to an external cryptographic resource.</t>
          <figure anchor="example-cryptoKeys-external">
            <name><tt>cryptoKeys</tt> example with external data</name>
            <sourcecode name="" type="json"><![CDATA[
"cryptoKeys": {
  "mykey1": {
    "uri": "https://www.example.com/keys/jdoe.cer"
  }
}
]]></sourcecode>
          </figure>
          <t>The following example shows how to embed key data in the CryptoKey.  The key data is depicted in multiple lines only for demonstration purposes.</t>
          <figure anchor="example-cryptoKeys-embedded">
            <name><tt>cryptoKeys</tt> example with embedded data</name>
            <sourcecode name="" type="json"><![CDATA[
"cryptoKeys": {
  "mykey2": {
    "uri": "data:application/pgp-keys;base64,LS0tLS1CRUdJTiBSU0EgUFVCTElDIEtF
            WS0tLS0tCk1JSUJDZ0tDQVFFQSt4R1ovd2N6OXVnRnBQMDdOc3BvNlUxN2wwWWhGa
            UZweHhVNHBUazNMaWZ6OVIzenNJc3UKRVJ3dGE3K2ZXSWZ4T28yMDhldHQvamhza2
            lWb2RTRXQzUUJHaDRYQmlweVdvcEt3WjkzSEhhRFZaQUFMaS8yQQoreFRCdFdkRW8
            3WEdVdWpLRHZDMi9hWkt1a2ZqcE9pVUk4QWhMQWZqbWxjRC9VWjFRUGgwbUhzZ2xS
            TkNtcEN3Cm13U1hBOVZObWh6K1BpQitEbWw0V1duS1cvVkhvMnVqVFh4cTcrZWZNV
            TRIMmZueTNTZTNLWU9zRlBGR1oxVE4KUVNZbEZ1U2hXckhQdGlMbVVkUG9QNkNWMm
            1NTDF0aytsN0RJSXFYclFoTFVLREFDZU01cm9NeDBrTGhVV0I4UAorMHVqMUNObE5
            ONEpSWmxDN3hGZnFpTWJGUlU5WjRONll3SURBUUFCCi0tLS0tRU5EIFJTQSBQVUJM
            SUMgS0VZLS0tLS0K"
  }
}
]]></sourcecode>
          </figure>
        </section>
        <section anchor="directories" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>directories</name>
          <t>Type: <tt>Id[Directory]</tt> (optional).</t>
          <t>These are directory service resources, such as entries in a directory or organizational directories for lookup.  A Directory object has all properties of the <xref target="resource">Resource</xref> data type, with the following additional definitions:</t>
          <ul>
            <li>The <tt>@type</tt> property value <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be <tt>Directory</tt>, if set.</li>
          </ul>
          <t>The <tt>kind</tt> property is mandatory.  Its <xref target="enumerated-values">enumerated</xref> values are:</t>
          <ul>
            <li><tt>directory</tt> The resource is a directory service where the entity represented by this Card is part of.  This typically is an organizational directory that also contains associated entities, e.g.,  co-workers and management in a company directory.</li>
            <li><tt>entry</tt> The resource is a directory entry of the entity represented by this Card.  In contrast to the <tt>directory</tt> type, this is the specific URI for the entity <em>within</em> a directory.</li>
          </ul>
          <t>In addition, the Directory object has the following property:</t>
          <ul>
            <li>listAs: <tt>UnsignedInt</tt> (optional).
          This defines the position of this directory resource in the list of all Directory objects having the same <tt>kind</tt> in this Card.  If set, the <tt>listAs</tt> value <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be higher than zero.  Multiple directory resources <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> have the same <tt>listAs</tt> property value, or none.  Sorting such entries is implementation-specific.
        </li>
          </ul>
          <figure anchor="example-directories">
            <name><tt>directories</tt> example</name>
            <sourcecode name="" type="json"><![CDATA[
"directories": {
  "dir1": {
    "kind": "entry",
    "uri": "https://dir.example.com/addrbook/jdoe/Jean%20Dupont.vcf"
  },
  "dir2": {
    "kind": "directory",
    "uri": "ldap://ldap.example/o=Example%20Tech,ou=Engineering",
    "pref": 1
  }
]]></sourcecode>
          </figure>
        </section>
        <section anchor="links" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>links</name>
          <t>Type: <tt>Id[Link]</tt> (optional).</t>
          <t>These are links to resources that do not fit any of the other use-case specific resource properties.  A Link object has all properties of the <xref target="resource">Resource</xref> data type, with the following additional definitions:</t>
          <ul>
            <li>The <tt>@type</tt> property value <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be <tt>Link</tt>, if set.</li>
          </ul>
          <t>The <tt>kind</tt> property is optional.  Its <xref target="enumerated-values">enumerated</xref> values are:</t>
          <ul>
            <li><tt>contact</tt> The resource is a URI by which the entity represented by this Card may be contacted, including web forms or other media that require user interaction.</li>
          </ul>
          <figure anchor="example-links">
            <name><tt>links</tt> example</name>
            <sourcecode name="" type="json"><![CDATA[
"links": {
  "link3": {
    "kind": "contact",
    "uri": "mailto:contact@example.com",
    "pref": 1
  }
}
]]></sourcecode>
          </figure>
        </section>
        <section anchor="media" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>media</name>
          <t>Type: <tt>Id[Media]</tt> (optional).</t>
          <t>These are media resources such as photographs, avatars, or sounds associated with the entity represented by this Card.  A Media object has all properties of the <xref target="resource">Resource</xref> data type, with the following additional definitions:</t>
          <ul>
            <li>The <tt>@type</tt> property value <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be <tt>Media</tt>, if set.</li>
          </ul>
          <t>The <tt>kind</tt> property is mandatory.  Its <xref target="enumerated-values">enumerated</xref> values are:</t>
          <ul>
            <li><tt>photo</tt> The resource is a photograph or avatar.</li>
            <li><tt>sound</tt> The resource is audio media, e.g.,  to specify the proper pronunciation of the name property contents.</li>
            <li><tt>logo</tt> The resource is a graphic image or logo associated with the entity represented by this Card.</li>
          </ul>
          <figure anchor="example-media">
            <name><tt>media</tt> example</name>
            <sourcecode name="" type="json"><![CDATA[
"media": {
  "res45": {
    "kind": "sound",
    "uri": "CID:JOHNQ.part8.19960229T080000.xyzMail@example.com"
  },
  "res47": {
    "kind": "logo",
    "uri": "https://www.example.com/pub/logos/abccorp.jpg"
  },
  "res1": {
    "kind": "photo",
    "uri": "data:image/jpeg;base64,/9j/4AAQSkZJRgABAQAASABIAAD/4..."
  }
}
]]></sourcecode>
          </figure>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section anchor="multilingual-properties" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Multilingual Properties</name>
        <t>This section defines properties how to localize the content of this Card in human languages.</t>
        <section anchor="localizations" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>localizations</name>
          <t>Type: String[PatchObject] (optional).</t>
          <t>This localizes property values in this Card to languages other than the main language.  Localizations provide language-specific alternatives for existing property values and <bcp14>SHOULD NOT</bcp14> add new properties.</t>
          <t>The keys in the localizations property object are language tags <xref target="RFC5646"/>. The values are patch objects which localize the Card in the respective language tag.  The paths in the PatchObject are relative to the Card that includes the <tt>localizations</tt> property.  A patch <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> target the <tt>localizations</tt> property.</t>
          <t>Conceptually, a Card is localized as follows:</t>
          <ul>
            <li>Determine the language tag in which this Card should be localized in.</li>
            <li>If the localizations property includes a key for that language, obtain the PatchObject value.  If there is no such key, stop.</li>
            <li>Create a copy of the Card, but do not copy the localizations property.</li>
            <li>Apply all patches in the PatchObject to the copy of the Card.</li>
            <li>Optionally, set the <tt>language</tt> property in the copy of the Card.</li>
            <li>Use the patched copy of the Card as the localized variant of the original Card.</li>
          </ul>
          <t>A patch in the PatchObject may contain any value type.  Its value <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be a valid value according to the definition of the patched property.</t>
          <t><xref target="example-localizations-replace"/> localizes the <tt>name</tt> property by completely replacing its contents in Ukrainian language with Cyrillic script.</t>
          <figure anchor="example-localizations-replace">
            <name>Example for localizing a top-level property</name>
            <artwork><![CDATA[
{
  "name": {
    "components": [
      { "kind": "title", "value": "Mr." },
      { "kind": "given", "value": "Ivan" },
      { "kind": "given2", "value": "Petrovich" },
      { "kind": "surname", "value": "Vasiliev" }
    ]
  },
  "localizations": {
    "uk-Cyrl": {
      "name": {
        "components": [
          { "kind": "title", "value": "г-н" },
          { "kind": "given", "value": "Иван" },
          { "kind": "given2", "value": "Петрович" },
          { "kind": "surname", "value": "Васильев" }
        ]
      }
    }
  }
}
]]></artwork>
          </figure>
          <t><xref target="example-localizations-patch"/> localizes the title name by patching <em>inside</em> the <tt>titles</tt> property.  All properties but the <tt>name</tt> property in the Title object are left as-is.</t>
          <figure anchor="example-localizations-patch">
            <name>Example for localizing a nested property</name>
            <artwork><![CDATA[
"name": {
  "full": "Gabriel García Márquez"
},
"titles": {
  "t1": {
    "kind": "title",
    "name": "novelist"
  }
},
"localizations": {
  "es": {
    "titles/t1/name": "autor"
  }
}
]]></artwork>
          </figure>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section anchor="additional-properties" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Additional Properties</name>
        <t>This section defines properties for which none of the previous sections are appropriate.</t>
        <section anchor="anniversaries" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>anniversaries</name>
          <t>Type : Id[Anniversary] (optional).</t>
          <t>These are memorable dates and events for the entity represented by this Card.  An Anniversary object has the following properties:</t>
          <ul spacing="normal">
            <li>@type: <tt>String</tt>.
              This <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be <tt>Anniversary</tt>, if set.
          </li>
            <li>
              <t>kind: <tt>String</tt> (mandatory).
              Specifies the kind of the anniversary.  The <xref target="enumerated-values">enumerated</xref> values are:
</t>
              <ul spacing="normal">
                <li><tt>birth</tt>: a birthday anniversary</li>
                <li><tt>death</tt>: a deathday anniversary</li>
                <li><tt>wedding</tt>: a wedding day anniversary</li>
              </ul>
            </li>
            <li>
              <t>date: <tt>PartialDate|Timestamp</tt> (mandatory, defaultType: <tt>PartialDate</tt>).</t>
              <t>The date of this anniversary in the Gregorian calendar.  This <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> either be a whole or partial calendar date or a complete UTC timestamp (see the definition of the Timestamp and PartialDate object types below).</t>
            </li>
            <li>place: Address (optional).
            An address associated with this anniversary, e.g.,  the place of birth or death.</li>
          </ul>
          <t>A PartialDate object represents a complete or partial calendar date in the Gregorian calendar.  It represents either a complete date, or a year, or a month in a year, or a day in a month.  It has the following properties, of which at least <tt>year</tt> or <tt>month</tt> and <tt>day</tt> <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be set:</t>
          <ul spacing="normal">
            <li>@type: <tt>String</tt>.
              This <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be <tt>PartialDate</tt>, if set.
          </li>
            <li>year: <tt>UnsignedInt</tt> (optional).  This is the calendar year.</li>
            <li>month: <tt>UnsignedInt</tt> (optional).  This is the calendar month, represented as the integers 1 &lt;= month &lt;= 12.  If this property is set then either <tt>year</tt> or <tt>day</tt> <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be set.</li>
            <li>day: <tt>UnsignedInt</tt> (optional).  This is the calendar month day, represented as the integers 1 &lt;= day &lt;= 31, depending on the validity within the month and year.  If this property is set then <tt>month</tt> <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be set.</li>
            <li>calendarScale: <tt>String</tt> (optional).  This is the calendar system in which this date occurs, in lowercase.  This <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be either a CLDR-registered calendar system name <xref target="RFC7529" format="default"/> or a vendor-specific value.  The year, month and day still <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be represented in the Gregorian calendar.  Note that the <tt>year</tt> property might be required to convert the date between the Gregorian calendar and the respective calendar system.</li>
          </ul>
          <t>A Timestamp object has the following properties:</t>
          <ul spacing="normal">
            <li>@type: <tt>String</tt>.
              This <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be <tt>Timestamp</tt>, if set.
          </li>
            <li>utc: <tt>UTCDateTime</tt> (mandatory).  Specifies the point in time in UTC time.
      </li>
          </ul>
          <t><xref target="example-anniversaries"/> illustrates anniversaries with partial dates and timestamp.  Note how the <tt>@type</tt> property is set for the <tt>Timestamp</tt> object value according to the rules defined <xref target="prop-type"/>.</t>
          <figure anchor="example-anniversaries">
            <name><tt>anniversaries</tt> example</name>
            <sourcecode name="" type="json"><![CDATA[
"anniversaries": {
  "k8": {
    "kind": "birth",
    "date": {
      "year": 1953,
      "month": 4,
      "day": 15
    }
  },
  "k9": {
    "kind": "death",
    "date": {
      "@type": "Timestamp",
      "utc": "2019-10-15T23:10:00Z"
    },
    "place": {
      "full": "4445 Tree Street\nNew England, ND 58647\nUSA"
    }
  }
}
]]></sourcecode>
          </figure>
        </section>
        <section anchor="keywords" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>keywords</name>
          <t>Type: <tt>String[Boolean]</tt> (optional).
A set of free-text keywords, also known as <em>tags</em>.  The set is represented as an object, with each key being a keyword.  The boolean value <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be <tt>true</tt>.</t>
          <figure anchor="example-keywords">
            <name><tt>keywords</tt> example</name>
            <sourcecode name="" type="json"><![CDATA[
"keywords": {
  "internet": true,
  "IETF": true
}
]]></sourcecode>
          </figure>
        </section>
        <section anchor="notes" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>notes</name>
          <t>Type: <tt>Id[Note]</tt> (optional).</t>
          <t>Free-text notes associated with this Card.  A Note object has the following properties:</t>
          <ul spacing="normal">
            <li>@type: <tt>String</tt>.
              This <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be <tt>Note</tt>, if set.
        </li>
            <li>
              <t>note: <tt>String</tt> (mandatory).  The free text value of this note.</t>
            </li>
            <li>
              <t>created: <tt>UTCDateTime</tt> (optional).  The date and time when this note was created.</t>
            </li>
            <li>
              <t>author: <tt>Author</tt> (optional).  The author of this note.</t>
            </li>
          </ul>
          <t>An Author object has the following properties, of which at least one other than <tt>@type</tt> <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be set:</t>
          <ul spacing="normal">
            <li>@type: <tt>String</tt>.
              This <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be <tt>Author</tt>, if set.
        </li>
            <li>
              <t>name: <tt>String</tt> (optional).  The name of this author.</t>
            </li>
            <li>
              <t>uri: <tt>String</tt> (optional).  A URI value that identifies the author.</t>
            </li>
          </ul>
          <figure anchor="example-notes">
            <name><tt>notes</tt> example</name>
            <sourcecode name="" type="json"><![CDATA[
"notes": {
  "n1": {
    "note": "Open office hours are 1600 to 1715 EST, Mon-Fri",
    "created": "2022-11-23T15:01:32Z",
    "author": {
      "name": "John"
    }
  }
}
]]></sourcecode>
          </figure>
        </section>
        <section anchor="personalInfo" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>personalInfo</name>
          <t>Type: <tt>Id[PersonalInfo]</tt> (optional).</t>
          <t>Defines personal information about the entity represented by this Card.
A PersonalInfo object has the following properties:</t>
          <ul spacing="normal">
            <li>@type: <tt>String</tt>.
              This <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be <tt>PersonalInfo</tt>, if set.
          </li>
            <li>
              <t>kind: <tt>String</tt> (mandatory).
              Specifies the kind of this personal information.  The <xref target="enumerated-values">enumerated</xref> values are:
</t>
              <ul spacing="normal">
                <li><tt>expertise</tt>: a field of expertise or credential</li>
                <li><tt>hobby</tt>: a hobby</li>
                <li><tt>interest</tt>: an interest</li>
              </ul>
            </li>
            <li>value: <tt>String</tt> (mandatory).
The actual information.</li>
            <li>
              <t>level: <tt>String</tt> (optional).
              Indicates the level of expertise, or engagement in hobby or interest.
                The <xref target="enumerated-values">enumerated</xref> values are:</t>
              <ul spacing="normal">
                <li>
                  <tt>high</tt>
                </li>
                <li>
                  <tt>medium</tt>
                </li>
                <li>
                  <tt>low</tt>
                </li>
              </ul>
            </li>
            <li>listAs: <tt>UnsignedInt</tt> (optional).
            This defines the position of this personal information in the list of all PersonalInfo objects having the same <tt>kind</tt> in this Card.  If set, the <tt>listAs</tt> value <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be higher than zero.  Multiple personal information entries <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> have the same <tt>listAs</tt> property value, or none.  Sorting such entries is implementation-specific.
        </li>
            <li>label: <tt>String</tt> (optional).
            A custom label.  See <xref target="prop-label"/>.</li>
          </ul>
          <figure anchor="example-personalInfo">
            <name><tt>personalInfo</tt> example</name>
            <sourcecode name="" type="json"><![CDATA[
"personalInfo": {
  "pi2": {
    "kind": "expertise",
    "value": "chemistry",
    "level": "high"
  },
  "pi1": {
    "kind": "hobby",
    "value": "reading",
    "level": "high"
  },
  "pi6": {
    "kind": "interest",
    "value": "r&b music",
    "level": "medium"
  }
}
]]></sourcecode>
          </figure>
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section anchor="implementation-status" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Implementation Status</name>
      <t>NOTE: Please remove this section and the reference to <xref target="RFC7942" format="default"/> prior
to publication as an RFC.
This section records the status of known implementations of the
format defined by this specification at the time of posting of this
Internet-Draft, and is based on a proposal described in
<xref target="RFC7942" format="default"/>.  The description of implementations in this section is
intended to assist the IETF in its decision processes in progressing
drafts to RFCs.  Please note that the listing of any individual
implementation here does not imply endorsement by the IETF.
Furthermore, no effort has been spent to verify the information
presented here that was supplied by IETF contributors.  This is not
intended as, and must not be construed to be, a catalog of available
implementations or their features.  Readers are advised to note that
other implementations may exist.
According to <xref target="RFC7942" format="default"/>, "this will allow reviewers and working groups
to assign due consideration to documents that have the benefit of
running code, which may serve as evidence of valuable experimentation
and feedback that have made the implemented protocols more mature.
It is up to the individual working groups to use this information as
they see fit".</t>
      <section anchor="implementation-iit-cnr-registro-it-rdap-server" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>IIT-CNR/Registro.it</name>
        <ul spacing="normal">
          <li>Responsible Organization: Institute of Informatics and Telematics
of National Research Council (IIT-CNR)/Registro.it</li>
          <li>Location: <eref target="https://rdap.pubtest.nic.it/domain/nic.it?jscard=1">https://rdap.pubtest.nic.it/</eref></li>
          <li>Description: This implementation includes support for RDAP queries
using data from the public test environment of .it ccTLD.  The RDAP server returns responses including JSContact Card in place of jCard when queries contain the parameter jscard=1.</li>
          <li>Level of Maturity: This is an "alpha" test implementation.</li>
          <li>Coverage: This implementation includes all features described in this specification.</li>
          <li>Contact Information: Mario Loffredo, mario.loffredo@iit.cnr.it</li>
        </ul>
      </section>
      <section anchor="implementation-cyrus-imap-server" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Cyrus IMAP</name>
        <ul spacing="normal">
          <li>Responsible Organization: The Cyrus Team</li>
          <li>Location: <eref target="https://github.com/cyrusimap/cyrus-imapd">https://github.com/cyrusimap/cyrus-imapd</eref></li>
          <li>Description: This implementation includes support for JSContact in its experimental JMAP for Addressbooks implementation.</li>
          <li>Level of Maturity: This is an "alpha" test implementation.</li>
          <li>Coverage: This implementation includes all features described in this specification.</li>
          <li>Contact Information: <eref target="https://cyrus.topicbox.com/groups/info">https://cyrus.topicbox.com/groups/info</eref></li>
        </ul>
      </section>
      <section anchor="implementation-audriga" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>OpenXPort JMAP iCalendar/vCard library</name>
        <ul spacing="normal">
          <li>Responsible Organization: audriga GmbH</li>
          <li>Location: <eref target="https://github.com/audriga/jmap-php-icalendar_vcard/">https://github.com/audriga/jmap-php-icalendar_vcard/</eref></li>
          <li>Description: This implementation includes support for converting vCard and JSContact.</li>
          <li>Level of Maturity: This is used in production systems.</li>
          <li>Coverage: This implementation includes some of the features described in this specification.</li>
          <li>Contact Information: <eref target="https://www.audriga.com">https://www.audriga.com</eref></li>
        </ul>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section anchor="iana-considerations" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>IANA Considerations</name>
      <section anchor="iana-media-type" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Media Type Registration</name>
        <t><xref target="I-D.ietf-calext-jscontact"/> defines a media type for use with JSContact data formatted in JSON.</t>
        <dl newline="true" spacing="normal">
          <dt>Type name:</dt>
          <dd>application</dd>
          <dt>Subtype name:</dt>
          <dd>jscontact+json</dd>
          <dt>Required parameters:</dt>
          <dd>
            <t>None</t>
          </dd>
          <dt>Optional parameters:</dt>
          <dd>
            <dl newline="false" spacing="normal">
              <dt>version</dt>
              <dd>This parameter conveys the version of the JSContact data in the body part.  It <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> occur more than once.  If this parameter is set, then the values of all JSContact <xref target="iana-property-registry-version"><tt>version</tt></xref> properties in the body part <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> match the parameter value.</dd>
            </dl>
          </dd>
          <dt>Encoding considerations:</dt>
          <dd>This is the same as the encoding considerations of application/json, as specified in <xref target="RFC8259" sectionFormat="of" section="11"/>.</dd>
          <dt>Security considerations:</dt>
          <dd> See <xref target="security-considerations" format="default"/> of <xref target="I-D.ietf-calext-jscontact"/>.</dd>
          <dt>Interoperability considerations:</dt>
          <dd>While JSContact is designed to avoid ambiguities as much as possible, when converting objects from other contact formats to/from JSContact, it is possible that differing representations for the same logical data or ambiguities in interpretation might arise.  The semantic equivalence of two JSContact objects may be determined differently by different applications, for example, where URL values differ in case between the two objects.</dd>
          <dt>Published specification:</dt>
          <dd>TBD</dd>
          <dt>Applications that use this media type:</dt>
          <dd>Applications that currently make use of the text/vcard media type can use this as an alternative.</dd>
          <dt>Fragment identifier considerations:</dt>
          <dd>A JSON Pointer fragment identifier may be used, as defined in <xref target="RFC6901" sectionFormat="comma" section="6"/>.</dd>
          <dt>Additional information:</dt>
          <dd>
            <dl newline="false" spacing="normal">
              <dt>Magic number(s):</dt>
              <dd>N/A</dd>
              <dt>File extensions(s):</dt>
              <dd>N/A</dd>
              <dt>Macintosh file type code(s):</dt>
              <dd>N/A</dd>
            </dl>
          </dd>
          <dt>Person &amp; email address to contact for further information:</dt>
          <dd>calsify@ietf.org</dd>
          <dt>Intended usage:</dt>
          <dd>COMMON</dd>
          <dt>Restrictions on usage:</dt>
          <dd>N/A</dd>
          <dt>Author:</dt>
          <dd>See the "Author's Address" section of <xref target="I-D.ietf-calext-jscontact"/>.</dd>
          <dt>Change controller:</dt>
          <dd>IETF</dd>
        </dl>
      </section>
      <section anchor="iana-jscontact-registry" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Creation of the "JSContact" Registry Group</name>
        <t>IANA is asked to create the "JSContact" registry group.  The new registry definitions in the following sections all belong to that group.</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="iana-registry-policy" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Registry Policy and Change Procedures</name>
        <t>Registry assignments that introduce <xref target="versioning">backwards-incompatible</xref> changes require the JSContact major version to change, other changes only require to change the minor version.  The registry policy for assignments that require the JSContact major version to change is Standards Action (<xref target="RFC8126" sectionFormat="comma" section="4.9"/>).  The registry policy for other assignments is Specification Required (<xref target="RFC8126" sectionFormat="comma" section="4.6"/>).</t>
        <t>The Designated Expert decides if a major or minor version change is required and assigns the new version to the <xref target="iana-version-registry">Version Registry</xref>.  Version numbers increment by one, and a major version change resets the minor version to zero.  An assignment may apply multiple changes and to more than one registry at once, in which case a single version change is sufficient.  If the registry policy is Specification Required, then the Designated Expert may decide that it is enough to document the new assignment in the Description item of the respective registry.</t>
        <t>A registration <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> have an intended usage of <tt>common</tt>, <tt>reserved</tt>, or <tt>obsolete</tt>.</t>
        <ul>
          <li>A <tt>common</tt> usage denotes an item with shared semantics and syntax across systems. Up-to-date systems <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> expect such items to occur in JSContact data.</li>
          <li>A <tt>reserved</tt> usage reserves an item in the registry without assigning semantics to avoid name collisions with future extensions or protocol use.</li>
          <li>An <tt>obsolete</tt> usage denotes an item that is no longer expected to be added by up-to-date systems.  A new assignment has probably been defined covering the obsolete item's semantics.</li>
        </ul>
        <t>The registration procedure is not a formal standards process but rather an administrative procedure intended to allow community comment and check whether it is coherent without excessive time delay.  It is designed to encourage vendors to document and register new items they add for use cases not covered by the original specification, leading to increased interoperability.</t>
        <section anchor="iana-registry-preliminary-community-review" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>Preliminary Community Review</name>
          <t>Notice of a potential new registration <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be sent to the Calext mailing list
	    &lt;calsify@ietf.org&gt; for review.  This mailing list is appropriate to solicit community feedback
	      on a proposed registry assignment.</t>
          <t>The intent of the public posting to this list is to solicit comments and feedback on the choice of
	    the item name or value, the unambiguity of its description, and a review of any
	      interoperability or security considerations.  The submitter may submit a revised registration proposal
	        or abandon the registration completely at any time.</t>
        </section>
        <section anchor="iana-registry-submit-request-to-iana" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>Submit Request to IANA</name>
          <t>Registration requests can be sent to &lt;iana@iana.org&gt;.</t>
        </section>
        <section anchor="iana-registry-designated-expert-review" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>Designated Expert Review</name>
          <t>The primary concern of the designated expert (DE) is preventing name collisions and encouraging
	    the submitter to document security and privacy considerations.  For a common-use registration, the DE
	      is expected to confirm that suitable documentation is available to ensure interoperability.
		  The DE should also verify that
            the new assignment does not conflict with work that is active or already published within the IETF.</t>
          <t>The DE will either approve or deny the registration request and publish a notice of the decision
	    to the Calext WG mailing list or its successor, as well as inform IANA.  A denial notice must be
	      justified by an explanation, and, in the cases where it is possible, concrete suggestions on how the
	        request can be modified to become acceptable should be provided.</t>
        </section>
        <section anchor="iana-registry-change-procedures" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>Change Procedures</name>
          <t>Once a JSContact registry group item has been published by IANA, the change controller may request a
	    change to its definition.  The same procedure that would be appropriate for the original registration
	      request is used to process a change request.</t>
          <t>JSContact registrations dot not get deleted; instead, items that are no longer believed appropriate for use are declared obsolete by a change to their "intended usage" field; such items will be clearly marked in the IANA registry.</t>
          <t>Significant changes to a JSContact registry item's definition should be requested only when there are
	    serious omissions or errors in the published specification, as such changes may cause
	      interoperability issues.  When review is required, a change request may be denied if it renders
	        entities that were valid under the previous definition invalid under the new definition.</t>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section anchor="iana-version-registry" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Creation of the "JSContact Version" Registry</name>
        <t>IANA is asked to create the "JSContact Version" registry.  The purpose of this new registry is to define the allowed value range of JSContact major and minor version numbers.</t>
        <t>The registry entries sort numerically ascending by the "Major Version" column.</t>
        <t>The registry process is outlined in <xref target="iana-registry-policy" format="default"/>.</t>
        <section anchor="iana-version-registry-template" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>"JSContact Version" Registry Template</name>
          <dl newline="false">
            <dt>Major Version:</dt>
            <dd>This is the numeric value of a JSContact major version number.  It <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be a positive integer.</dd>
            <dt>Highest Minor Version:</dt>
            <dd> This is the maximum numeric value of a JSContact minor version for the given major version.  It <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be zero or a positive integer.  All numbers less than or equal this value are valid minor version values for the given major version.</dd>
          </dl>
        </section>
        <section anchor="iana-version-registry-contents" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>Initial Contents for the "JSContact Version" Registry</name>
          <t>The following table lists the initial valid major and minor version number ranges.</t>
          <table anchor="tab-iana-version-registry" align="center">
            <name>JSContact Versions</name>
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <th align="left">Major Version</th>
                <th align="left">Highest Minor Version</th>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">1</td>
                <td align="left">0</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section anchor="iana-property-registry" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Creation of the "JSContact Properties" Registry</name>
        <t>IANA is asked to create the "JSContact Properties" registry.  The purpose of this new registry is to allow interoperability of extensions to JSContact objects</t>
        <t>The registry entries sort alphabetically ascending by the "Property Name" column first, "Property Context" second, "Since Version" third.  Equal entries sort in any order.</t>
        <t>The registry process for a new property is outlined in <xref target="iana-registry-policy" format="default"/>.</t>
        <section anchor="iana-property-registry-template" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>"JSContact Properties" Registry Template</name>
          <dl newline="false">
            <dt>Property Name:</dt>
            <dd>This is the name of the property.  The property name <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> already be
		    registered for
		        any of the object types listed in the "Property Context" field of this registration.  Other object
			    types <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> already have registered a different property with the same name; however,
			        the same name <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> only be used when the semantics are analogous.</dd>
            <dt>Property Type:</dt>
            <dd> This is the type of this property, using type signatures, as specified in <xref target="type-signatures" format="default"/>.
		    The property type <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be registered in the "JSContact Types" registry.</dd>
            <dt>Property Context:</dt>
            <dd>This is a comma-separated list of JSContact object types (<xref target="iana-type-registry-contents"/>) that contain this property.</dd>
            <dt>Reference or Description:</dt>
            <dd>This is a brief description or RFC number and section reference where the property is specified (omitted for "reserved" property names). This must include references to all RFC documents where this property is introduced or updated.</dd>
            <dt>Intended Usage:</dt>
            <dd>This may be "common", "reserved", or "obsolete".</dd>
            <dt>Since Version:</dt>
            <dd>This defines the JSContact version on which this property definition is based on.  The version <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be one of the allowed values of the <tt>version</tt> property in the JSContact Enum Value registry (see <xref target="tab-iana-version-registry"/>).</dd>
            <dt>Until Version:</dt>
            <dd>This defines the JSContact version after which this property got obsoleted and <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> be used in later versions.  The Until Version value either <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> be set, or be one of the allowed values of the <tt>version</tt> property in the JSContact Enum Value registry (see <xref target="tab-iana-version-registry"/>).</dd>
            <dt>Change Controller:</dt>
            <dd>This is who may request a change to this entry's definition (<tt>IETF</tt> for RFCs from the IETF stream).</dd>
          </dl>
        </section>
        <section anchor="iana-property-registry-contents" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>Initial Contents for the "JSContact Properties" Registry</name>
          <t>The following table lists the initial <tt>common</tt> usage entries of the "JSContact Properties" registry.  The Since Version for all properties is <tt>1.0</tt>.  The Until Version for all properties is not set.  All RFC section references are for <xref target="I-D.ietf-calext-jscontact"/>.  The change controller for all these properties is <tt>IETF</tt>.</t>
          <table anchor="tab-iana-property-registry" align="center">
            <name>JSContact Properties with "common" usage</name>
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <th align="left">Property Name</th>
                <th align="left">Property Type</th>
                <th align="left">Property Context</th>
                <th align="left">Reference or Description</th>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <!-- Everything in here should be sorted alphabetically: table entries by property name, the references for each property alphabetically by the object type or property they refer to -->
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">@type</td>
                <td align="left">String</td>
                <td align="left">Address, AddressComponent, Anniversary, Author, Card, Calendar,  CryptoKey, Directory, EmailAddress, LanguagePref, Link, Media, Name, NameComponent, Nickname, Note, OnlineService, Organization, OrgUnit, PartialDate,PersonalInfo, Phone, Pronouns, Relation, Resource, SchedulingAddress, SpeakToAs, Timestamp, Title</td>
                <td align="left"><xref target="addresses" format="default"/>, <xref target="anniversaries" format="default"/>, <xref target="cardtype" format="default"/>, <xref target="calendars" format="default"/>, <xref target="cryptoKeys" format="default"/>, <xref target="directories" format="default"/>, <xref target="emails" format="default"/>, <xref target="preferredLanguages" format="default"/>, <xref target="links" format="default"/>, <xref target="media" format="default"/>, <xref target="name" format="default"/>, <xref target="nicknames" format="default"/>, <xref target="notes" format="default"/>, <xref target="onlineServices" format="default"/>, <xref target="organizations" format="default"/>, <xref target="personalInfo" format="default"/>, <xref target="phones" format="default"/>, <xref target="speakToAs" format="default"/>, <xref target="relatedTo" format="default"/>, <xref target="schedulingAddresses" format="default"/>, <xref target="titles" format="default"/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr anchor="iana-property-registry-version">
                <td align="left">version</td>
                <td align="left">String</td>
                <td align="left">Card</td>
                <td align="left">
                  <xref target="prop-version" format="default"/>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">address</td>
                <td align="left">String</td>
                <td align="left">EmailAddress</td>
                <td align="left">
                  <xref target="emails" format="default"/>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">addresses</td>
                <td align="left">Id[Address]</td>
                <td align="left">Card</td>
                <td align="left">
                  <xref target="addresses" format="default"/>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">anniversaries</td>
                <td align="left">Id[Anniversary]</td>
                <td align="left">Card</td>
                <td align="left">
                  <xref target="anniversaries" format="default"/>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">author</td>
                <td align="left">Author</td>
                <td align="left">Note</td>
                <td align="left">
                  <xref target="notes" format="default"/>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">calendars</td>
                <td align="left">Id[Calendar]</td>
                <td align="left">Card</td>
                <td align="left">
                  <xref target="calendars" format="default"/>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">calendarScale</td>
                <td align="left">String</td>
                <td align="left">PartialDate</td>
                <td align="left">
                  <xref target="anniversaries" format="default"/>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">components</td>
                <td align="left">AddressComponent[]</td>
                <td align="left">Address</td>
                <td align="left">
                  <xref target="addresses" format="default"/>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">components</td>
                <td align="left">NameComponent[]</td>
                <td align="left">Name</td>
                <td align="left">
                  <xref target="name" format="default"/>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">contexts</td>
                <td align="left">String[Boolean]</td>
                <td align="left">Address, Calendar,  CryptoKey, Directory, EmailAddress, LanguagePref, Link, Media, Nickname, OnlineService, Organization, Phone, Pronouns, SchedulingAddress</td>
                <td align="left"><xref target="prop-contexts" format="default"/>, <xref target="addresses" format="default"/>, <xref target="calendars" format="default"/>, <xref target="cryptoKeys" format="default"/>, <xref target="directories" format="default"/>, <xref target="emails" format="default"/>, <xref target="preferredLanguages" format="default"/>, <xref target="links" format="default"/>, <xref target="media" format="default"/>, <xref target="nicknames" format="default"/>, <xref target="onlineServices" format="default"/>, <xref target="organizations" format="default"/>, <xref target="phones" format="default"/>, <xref target="speakToAs" format="default"/>, <xref target="schedulingAddresses" format="default"/><xref target="resource" format="default"/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">coordinates</td>
                <td align="left">String</td>
                <td align="left">Address</td>
                <td align="left">
                  <xref target="addresses" format="default"/>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">countryCode</td>
                <td align="left">String</td>
                <td align="left">Address</td>
                <td align="left">
                  <xref target="addresses" format="default"/>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">created</td>
                <td align="left">UTCDateTime</td>
                <td align="left">Card, Note</td>
                <td align="left"><xref target="created" format="default"/>, <xref target="notes" format="default"/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">date</td>
                <td align="left">PartialDate|Timestamp</td>
                <td align="left">Anniversary</td>
                <td align="left">
                  <xref target="anniversaries" format="default"/>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">day</td>
                <td align="left">UnsignedInt</td>
                <td align="left">PartialDate</td>
                <td align="left">
                  <xref target="anniversaries" format="default"/>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">defaultSeparator</td>
                <td align="left">String</td>
                <td align="left">Address, Name</td>
                <td align="left"><xref target="addresses" format="default"/>,
                  <xref target="name" format="default"/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">directories</td>
                <td align="left">Id[Directory]</td>
                <td align="left">Card</td>
                <td align="left">
                  <xref target="directories" format="default"/>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">emails</td>
                <td align="left">Id[EmailAddress]</td>
                <td align="left">Card</td>
                <td align="left">
                  <xref target="emails" format="default"/>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">features</td>
                <td align="left">String[Boolean]</td>
                <td align="left">Phone</td>
                <td align="left">
                  <xref target="phones" format="default"/>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">full</td>
                <td align="left">String</td>
                <td align="left">Address, Name</td>
                <td align="left"><xref target="addresses" format="default"/>,
                  <xref target="name" format="default"/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">grammaticalGender</td>
                <td align="left">String</td>
                <td align="left">SpeakToAs</td>
                <td align="left">
                  <xref target="speakToAs" format="default"/>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">isOrdered</td>
                <td align="left">Boolean</td>
                <td align="left">Address, Name</td>
                <td align="left"><xref target="addresses" format="default"/>,
                  <xref target="name" format="default"/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">keywords</td>
                <td align="left">String[Boolean]</td>
                <td align="left">Card</td>
                <td align="left">
                  <xref target="keywords" format="default"/>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">kind</td>
                <td align="left">String</td>
                <td align="left">Card</td>
                <td align="left">
                  <xref target="kind" format="default"/>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">kind</td>
                <td align="left">String</td>
                <td align="left">Anniversary, Calendar, Card, CryptoKey, Directory, Link, Media, NameComponent, PersonalInfo, AddressComponent, Title</td>
                <td align="left"><xref target="anniversaries" format="default"/>, <xref target="calendars" format="default"/>, <xref target="kind" format="default"/>, <xref target="cryptoKeys" format="default"/>, <xref target="directories" format="default"/>, <xref target="links" format="default"/>, <xref target="media" format="default"/>, <xref target="name" format="default"/>, <xref target="personalInfo" format="default"/>, <xref target="addresses" format="default"/>, <xref target="titles" format="default"/>, <xref target="resource" format="default"/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">label</td>
                <td align="left">String</td>
                <td align="left">Calendar, CryptoKey, Directory, EmailAddress, Link, Media, OnlineService, PersonalInfo, Phone, SchedulingAddress</td>
                <td align="left"><xref target="prop-label" format="default"/>, <xref target="calendars" format="default"/>, <xref target="cryptoKeys" format="default"/>, <xref target="directories" format="default"/>, <xref target="emails" format="default"/>, <xref target="links" format="default"/>, <xref target="media" format="default"/>, <xref target="onlineServices" format="default"/>, <xref target="personalInfo" format="default"/>, <xref target="phones" format="default"/>, <xref target="schedulingAddresses" format="default"/>, <xref target="resource" format="default"/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">language</td>
                <td align="left">String</td>
                <td align="left">Card, LanguagePref</td>
                <td align="left"><xref target="language" format="default"/>,
                  <xref target="preferredLanguages" format="default"/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">level</td>
                <td align="left">String</td>
                <td align="left">PersonalInfo</td>
                <td align="left">
                  <xref target="personalInfo" format="default"/>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">links</td>
                <td align="left">Id[Link]</td>
                <td align="left">Card</td>
                <td align="left">
                  <xref target="links" format="default"/>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">listAs</td>
                <td align="left">UnsignedInt</td>
                <td align="left">Directory, PersonalInfo</td>
                <td align="left"><xref target="directories" format="default"/>, <xref target="personalInfo" format="default"/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">localizations</td>
                <td align="left">String[PatchObject]</td>
                <td align="left">Card</td>
                <td align="left">
                  <xref target="localizations" format="default"/>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">media</td>
                <td align="left">Id[Media]</td>
                <td align="left">Card</td>
                <td align="left">
                  <xref target="media" format="default"/>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">mediaType</td>
                <td align="left">String</td>
                <td align="left">Calendar, CryptoKey, Directory, Link, Media</td>
                <td align="left"><xref target="resource" format="default"/>, <xref target="calendars" format="default"/>, <xref target="cryptoKeys" format="default"/>, <xref target="directories" format="default"/>, <xref target="links" format="default"/>, <xref target="media" format="default"/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">members</td>
                <td align="left">String[Boolean]</td>
                <td align="left">Card</td>
                <td align="left">
                  <xref target="members" format="default"/>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">month</td>
                <td align="left">UnsignedInt</td>
                <td align="left">PartialDate</td>
                <td align="left">
                  <xref target="anniversaries" format="default"/>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">name</td>
                <td align="left">Name</td>
                <td align="left">Card</td>
                <td align="left">
                  <xref target="name" format="default"/>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">name</td>
                <td align="left">String</td>
                <td align="left">Author, Nickname, Organization, OrgUnit, Title</td>
                <td align="left"><xref target="notes" format="default"/>, <xref target="nicknames" format="default"/>, <xref target="organizations" format="default"/>, <xref target="titles" format="default"/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">nicknames</td>
                <td align="left">Id[Nickname]</td>
                <td align="left">Card</td>
                <td align="left">
                  <xref target="nicknames" format="default"/>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">note</td>
                <td align="left">String</td>
                <td align="left">Note</td>
                <td align="left">
                  <xref target="notes" format="default"/>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">notes</td>
                <td align="left">Id[Note]</td>
                <td align="left">Card</td>
                <td align="left">
                  <xref target="notes" format="default"/>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">number</td>
                <td align="left">String</td>
                <td align="left">Phone</td>
                <td align="left">
                  <xref target="phones" format="default"/>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">onlineServices</td>
                <td align="left">Id[OnlineService]</td>
                <td align="left">Card</td>
                <td align="left">
                  <xref target="onlineServices" format="default"/>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">organization</td>
                <td align="left">String</td>
                <td align="left">Title</td>
                <td align="left">
                  <xref target="titles" format="default"/>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">organizations</td>
                <td align="left">Id[Organization]</td>
                <td align="left">Card</td>
                <td align="left">
                  <xref target="organizations" format="default"/>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">personalInfo</td>
                <td align="left">Id[PersonalInfo]</td>
                <td align="left">Card</td>
                <td align="left">
                  <xref target="personalInfo" format="default"/>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">phones</td>
                <td align="left">Id[Phone]</td>
                <td align="left">Card</td>
                <td align="left">
                  <xref target="phones" format="default"/>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">phonetic</td>
                <td align="left">String</td>
                <td align="left">AddressComponent, NameComponent</td>
                <td align="left"><xref target="addresscomponent" format="default"/>,
                  <xref target="namecomponent" format="default"/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">phoneticScript</td>
                <td align="left">String</td>
                <td align="left">Address, Name</td>
                <td align="left"><xref target="name" format="default"/>,
                  <xref target="addresses" format="default"/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">phoneticSystem</td>
                <td align="left">String</td>
                <td align="left">Address, Name</td>
                <td align="left"><xref target="name" format="default"/>,
                  <xref target="addresses" format="default"/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">place</td>
                <td align="left">Address</td>
                <td align="left">Anniversary</td>
                <td align="left">
                  <xref target="anniversaries" format="default"/>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">pref</td>
                <td align="left">UnsignedInt</td>
                <td align="left">Address, Calendar,  CryptoKey, Directory, EmailAddress, LanguagePref, Link, Media, Nickname, OnlineService, Phone, Pronouns, SchedulingAddress</td>
                <td align="left"><xref target="prop-pref" format="default"/>, <xref target="addresses" format="default"/>, <xref target="calendars" format="default"/>, <xref target="cryptoKeys" format="default"/>, <xref target="directories" format="default"/>, <xref target="emails" format="default"/>, <xref target="preferredLanguages" format="default"/>, <xref target="links" format="default"/>, <xref target="media" format="default"/>, <xref target="nicknames" format="default"/>, <xref target="onlineServices" format="default"/>, <xref target="phones" format="default"/>, <xref target="speakToAs" format="default"/>, <xref target="schedulingAddresses" format="default"/>, <xref target="resource" format="default"/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">preferredLanguages</td>
                <td align="left">String[LanguagePref[]]</td>
                <td align="left">Card</td>
                <td align="left">
                  <xref target="preferredLanguages" format="default"/>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">prodId</td>
                <td align="left">String</td>
                <td align="left">Card</td>
                <td align="left">
                  <xref target="prodId" format="default"/>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">pronouns</td>
                <td align="left">Id[Pronouns]</td>
                <td align="left">SpeakToAs</td>
                <td align="left">
                  <xref target="speakToAs" format="default"/>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">relatedTo</td>
                <td align="left">String[Relation]</td>
                <td align="left">Card</td>
                <td align="left">
                  <xref target="relatedTo" format="default"/>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">relation</td>
                <td align="left">String[Boolean]</td>
                <td align="left">Relation</td>
                <td align="left">
                  <xref target="relatedTo" format="default"/>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">schedulingAddresses</td>
                <td align="left">Id[SchedulingAddress]</td>
                <td align="left">Card</td>
                <td align="left">
                  <xref target="schedulingAddresses" format="default"/>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">service</td>
                <td align="left">String</td>
                <td align="left">OnlineService</td>
                <td align="left">
                  <xref target="onlineServices" format="default"/>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">sortAs</td>
                <td align="left">String[String]</td>
                <td align="left">Name</td>
                <td align="left">
                  <xref target="name" format="default"/>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">sortAs</td>
                <td align="left">String</td>
                <td align="left">Organization, OrgUnit</td>
                <td align="left">
                  <xref target="organizations" format="default"/>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">speakToAs</td>
                <td align="left">SpeakToAs</td>
                <td align="left">Card</td>
                <td align="left">
                  <xref target="speakToAs" format="default"/>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">timeZone</td>
                <td align="left">String</td>
                <td align="left">Address</td>
                <td align="left">
                  <xref target="addresses" format="default"/>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">titles</td>
                <td align="left">Id[Title]</td>
                <td align="left">Card</td>
                <td align="left">
                  <xref target="titles" format="default"/>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">uid</td>
                <td align="left">String</td>
                <td align="left">Card</td>
                <td align="left">
                  <xref target="uid" format="default"/>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">units</td>
                <td align="left">OrgUnit[]</td>
                <td align="left">Organization</td>
                <td align="left">
                  <xref target="organizations" format="default"/>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">updated</td>
                <td align="left">UTCDateTime</td>
                <td align="left">Card</td>
                <td align="left">
                  <xref target="updated" format="default"/>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">uri</td>
                <td align="left">String</td>
                <td align="left">Author, Calendar, CryptoKey, Directory, Link, Media, OnlineService, SchedulingAddress</td>
                <td align="left"><xref target="notes" format="default"/>, <xref target="resource" format="default"/>, <xref target="calendars" format="default"/>, <xref target="cryptoKeys" format="default"/>, <xref target="directories" format="default"/>, <xref target="links" format="default"/>, <xref target="media" format="default"/>, <xref target="onlineServices" format="default"/>, <xref target="schedulingAddresses" format="default"/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">user</td>
                <td align="left">String</td>
                <td align="left">OnlineService</td>
                <td align="left">
                  <xref target="onlineServices" format="default"/>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">utc</td>
                <td align="left">UTCDateTime</td>
                <td align="left">Timestamp</td>
                <td align="left">
                  <xref target="anniversaries" format="default"/>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">value</td>
                <td align="left">String</td>
                <td align="left">AddressComponent, NameComponent, PersonalInfo</td>
                <td align="left"><xref target="addresses" format="default"/>,
                  <xref target="name" format="default"/>,
                  <xref target="personalInfo" format="default"/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">year</td>
                <td align="left">UnsignedInt</td>
                <td align="left">PartialDate</td>
                <td align="left">
                  <xref target="anniversaries" format="default"/>
                </td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
          <t>The following table lists the initial <tt>reserved</tt> usage entries of the "JSContact Properties" registry.  All RFC section references are for <xref target="I-D.ietf-calext-jscontact"/>.  The change controller for all these properties is <tt>IETF</tt>.</t>
          <table anchor="tab-iana-reserved-property-registry" align="center">
            <name>JSContact Properties with "reserved" usage</name>
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <th align="left">Property Name</th>
                <th align="left">Property Type</th>
                <th align="left">Property Context</th>
                <th align="left">Reference or Description</th>
                <th align="left">Intended Usage</th>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <!-- Everything in here should be sorted alphabetically: table entries by property name, the references for each property alphabetically by the object type or property they refer to -->
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">extra</td>
                <td align="left">not applicable</td>
                <td align="left">not applicable</td>
                <td align="left">
                  <xref target="reserved-prop-names" format="default"/>
                </td>
                <td align="left">reserved</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section anchor="iana-type-registry" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Creation of the "JSContact Types" Registry</name>
        <t>IANA is asked to create the "JSContact Types" registry.  The purpose of this new registry is to avoid name collisions for JSContact type names and provide a complete reference for all data types used for JSContact property values.</t>
        <t>The registry entries sort alphabetically ascending by the "Type Name" column.  Equal entries sort in any order.</t>
        <t>The registry process for a new type is outlined in <xref target="iana-registry-policy" format="default"/>.</t>
        <section anchor="iana-type-registry-template" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>"JSContact Types" Registry Template</name>
          <dl newline="false">
            <dt>Type Name:</dt>
            <dd>the name of the type</dd>
            <dt>Reference or Description:</dt>
            <dd>a brief description or RFC number and section reference where the Type is specified (may be omitted for "reserved" type names)</dd>
            <dt>Intended Usage:</dt>
            <dd>common, reserved, or obsolete</dd>
            <dt>Since Version:</dt>
            <dd>This defines the JSContact version on which this type definition is based on.  The version <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be one of the allowed values of the <tt>version</tt> property in the JSContact Enum Value registry (see <xref target="tab-iana-version-registry"/>).</dd>
            <dt>Until Version:</dt>
            <dd>This defines the JSContact version after which this type definition got obsoleted and <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> be used in later versions.  The Until Version value either <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be not set, or one of the allowed values of the <tt>version</tt> property in the JSContact Enum Value registry (see <xref target="tab-iana-version-registry"/>).</dd>
            <dt>Change Controller:</dt>
            <dd>This is who may request a change to this entry's definition (<tt>IETF</tt> for RFCs from the IETF stream).</dd>
          </dl>
        </section>
        <section anchor="iana-type-registry-contents" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>Initial Contents for the "JSContact Types" Registry</name>
          <t>The following table lists the initial <tt>common</tt> usage entries of the JSContact Types registry.  The Since Version for all types is <tt>1.0</tt>.  The Until Version for all types is not set.  All RFC section references are for <xref target="I-D.ietf-calext-jscontact"/>.  The change controller for all these properties is <tt>IETF</tt>.</t>
          <table anchor="tab-iana-type-registry-common" align="left">
            <name>JSContact Types with "common" usage</name>
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <th align="left">Type Name</th>
                <th align="left">Reference or Description</th>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">Address</td>
                <td align="left">
                  <xref target="addresses" format="default"/>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">AddressComponent</td>
                <td align="left">
                  <xref target="addresses" format="default"/>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">Anniversary</td>
                <td align="left">
                  <xref target="anniversaries" format="default"/>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">Author</td>
                <td align="left">
                  <xref target="notes" format="default"/>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">Boolean</td>
                <td align="left">
                  <xref target="type-signatures" format="default"/>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">Calendar</td>
                <td align="left">
                  <xref target="calendars" format="default"/>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">Card</td>
                <td align="left">
                  <xref target="card" format="default"/>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">CryptoKey</td>
                <td align="left">
                  <xref target="cryptoKeys" format="default"/>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">Directory</td>
                <td align="left">
                  <xref target="directories" format="default"/>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">EmailAddress</td>
                <td align="left">
                  <xref target="emails" format="default"/>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">Id</td>
                <td align="left">
                  <xref target="id" format="default"/>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">Int</td>
                <td align="left">
                  <xref target="int-unsignedint" format="default"/>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">LanguagePref</td>
                <td align="left">
                  <xref target="preferredLanguages" format="default"/>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">Link</td>
                <td align="left">
                  <xref target="links" format="default"/>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">Media</td>
                <td align="left">
                  <xref target="media" format="default"/>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">Name</td>
                <td align="left">
                  <xref target="name" format="default"/>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">NameComponent</td>
                <td align="left">
                  <xref target="name" format="default"/>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">Nickname</td>
                <td align="left">
                  <xref target="nicknames" format="default"/>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">Note</td>
                <td align="left">
                  <xref target="notes" format="default"/>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">Number</td>
                <td align="left">
                  <xref target="type-signatures" format="default"/>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">OnlineService</td>
                <td align="left">
                  <xref target="onlineServices" format="default"/>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">Organization</td>
                <td align="left">
                  <xref target="organizations" format="default"/>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">OrgUnit</td>
                <td align="left">
                  <xref target="organizations" format="default"/>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">PartialDate</td>
                <td align="left">
                  <xref target="anniversaries" format="default"/>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">PatchObject</td>
                <td align="left">
                  <xref target="patchobject" format="default"/>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">PersonalInfo</td>
                <td align="left">
                  <xref target="personalInfo" format="default"/>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">Phone</td>
                <td align="left">
                  <xref target="phones" format="default"/>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">Pronouns</td>
                <td align="left">
                  <xref target="speakToAs" format="default"/>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">Relation</td>
                <td align="left">
                  <xref target="relatedTo" format="default"/>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">SchedulingAddress</td>
                <td align="left">
                  <xref target="schedulingAddresses" format="default"/>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">SpeakToAs</td>
                <td align="left">
                  <xref target="speakToAs" format="default"/>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">String</td>
                <td align="left">
                  <xref target="type-signatures" format="default"/>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">Timestamp</td>
                <td align="left">
                  <xref target="anniversaries" format="default"/>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">Title</td>
                <td align="left">
                  <xref target="titles" format="default"/>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">UnsignedInt</td>
                <td align="left">
                  <xref target="int-unsignedint" format="default"/>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">UTCDateTime</td>
                <td align="left">
                  <xref target="utcdatetime" format="default"/>
                </td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
          <t>The following table lists the initial <tt>reserved</tt> usage entries of the JSContact Types registry.  All types are for version <tt>1.0</tt>.  All RFC section references are for <xref target="I-D.ietf-calext-jscontact"/>.  The change controller for all these properties is <tt>IETF</tt>.</t>
          <table anchor="tab-iana-type-registry-reserved" align="left">
            <name>JSContact Types with "reserved" usage</name>
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <th align="left">Type Name</th>
                <th align="left">Reference or Description</th>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">Resource</td>
                <td align="left">
                  <xref target="resource" format="default"/>
                </td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section anchor="iana-enum-registry" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Creation of the "JSContact Enum Values" Registry</name>
        <t>IANA is asked to create the "JSContact Enum Values" registry.  The purpose of the new registry is  to allow interoperable extension of semantics for JSContact properties with enumerable values.  Each such property will have a subregistry of allowed values.</t>
        <t>The registry entries sort alphabetically ascending by the "Property Name" column first, "Property Context" second, "Since Version" third.  The enum values sort alphabetically ascending.  Equal entries sort in any order.</t>
        <t>The registry process for a new enum value or adding a new enumerable property is outlined in <xref target="iana-registry-policy" format="default"/>.</t>
        <section anchor="iana-enum-registry-registry-template" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>"JSContact Enum Values" Registry Property Template</name>
          <t>This template is for adding a subregistry for a new enumerable property to the "JSContact Enum" registry.</t>
          <dl newline="false">
            <dt>Property Name:</dt>
            <dd>These are the name(s) of the property or properties where these values may be used.  This <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be registered in the "JSContact Properties" registry.</dd>
            <dt>Context:</dt>
            <dd>This is the list of allowed object types where the property or properties may appear, as registered in the "JSContact Properties" registry.  This disambiguates where there may be two distinct properties with the same name in different contexts.</dd>
            <dt>Since Version:</dt>
            <dd>This defines the JSContact version on which this enum value definition is based on.  The version <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be one of the allowed values of the <tt>version</tt> property in the JSContact Enum Value registry (see <xref target="tab-iana-version-registry"/>).</dd>
            <dt>Until Version:</dt>
            <dd>This defines the JSContact version after which this enum value definition got obsoleted and <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> be used in later versions.  The Until Version value either <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be not set, or one of the allowed values of the <tt>version</tt> property in the JSContact Enum Value registry (see <xref target="tab-iana-version-registry"/>).</dd>
            <dt>Change Controller:</dt>
            <dd>This is who may request a change to this entry's definition (<tt>IETF</tt> for RFCs from the IETF stream).</dd>
            <dt>Initial Contents:</dt>
            <dd>This is the initial list of defined values for this enum, using the template defined in <xref target="iana-enum-registry-value-template" format="default"/>.  A subregistry will be created with these values for this property name/context tuple.</dd>
          </dl>
        </section>
        <section anchor="iana-enum-registry-value-template" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>"JSContact Enum Values" Registry Value Template</name>
          <t>This template is for adding a new enum value to a subregistry in the JSContact Enum registry.</t>
          <dl newline="false">
            <dt>Enum Value:</dt>
            <dd>The verbatim value of the enum</dd>
            <dt>Reference or Description:</dt>
            <dd>A brief description or RFC number and section reference for the semantics of this value</dd>
            <dt>Since Version:</dt>
            <dd>The JSContact version on which the enum value definition is based on.  The version <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be one of the allowed values of the <tt>version</tt> property in the JSContact Enum Value registry (see <xref target="tab-iana-version-registry"/>).</dd>
            <dt>Until Version:</dt>
            <dd>The JSContact version after which this enum value got obsoleted and <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> be used in later versions.  The Until Version value either <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be not set, or one of the allowed values of the <tt>version</tt> property in the JSContact Enum Value registry (see <xref target="tab-iana-version-registry"/>).</dd>
          </dl>
        </section>
        <section anchor="iana-enum-registry-contents" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>Initial Contents for the "JSContact Enum Values" Registry</name>
          <t>For each subregistry created in this section, all RFC section references are for <xref target="I-D.ietf-calext-jscontact"/>.  For all entries, the Since Version is <tt>1.0</tt>, the Until Version is not set, the Change Controller is <tt>IETF</tt>.</t>
          <dl spacing="compact" newline="false" indent="20">
            <dt>Property Name:</dt>
            <dd>contexts</dd>
            <dt>Context:</dt>
            <dd>Address</dd>
            <dt>Initial Contents:</dt>
            <dd>
              <table anchor="tab-iana-enum-addr-contexts" align="left">
                <name>JSContact Enum Values for contexts (Context: Address)</name>
                <thead>
                  <tr>
                    <th align="left">Enum Value</th>
                    <th align="left">Reference or Description</th>
                  </tr>
                </thead>
                <tbody>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">billing</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="addresses" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">delivery</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="addresses" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">private</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="prop-contexts" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">work</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="prop-contexts" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                </tbody>
              </table>
            </dd>
          </dl>
          <dl spacing="compact" newline="false" indent="20">
            <dt>Property Name:</dt>
            <dd>contexts</dd>
            <dt>Context:</dt>
            <dd>Calendar,  CryptoKey, Directory, EmailAddress, LanguagePref, Link, Media, Nickname, OnlineService, Phone, Pronouns, SchedulingAddress</dd>
            <dt>Initial Contents:</dt>
            <dd>
              <table anchor="tab-iana-enum-contexts" align="left">
                <name>JSContact Enum Values for contexts (Context: Calendar,  CryptoKey, Directory, EmailAddress, LanguagePref, Link, Media, Nickname, OnlineService, Phone, Pronouns, SchedulingAddress)</name>
                <thead>
                  <tr>
                    <th align="left">Enum Value</th>
                    <th align="left">Reference or Description</th>
                  </tr>
                </thead>
                <tbody>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">private</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="prop-contexts" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">work</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="prop-contexts" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                </tbody>
              </table>
            </dd>
          </dl>
          <dl spacing="compact" newline="false" indent="20">
            <dt>Property Name:</dt>
            <dd>features</dd>
            <dt>Context:</dt>
            <dd>Phone</dd>
            <dt>Initial Contents:</dt>
            <dd>
              <table anchor="tab-iana-enum-phone-features" align="left">
                <name>JSContact Enum Values for features (Context: Phone)</name>
                <thead>
                  <tr>
                    <th align="left">Enum Value</th>
                    <th align="left">Reference or Description</th>
                  </tr>
                </thead>
                <tbody>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">fax</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="phones" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">main-number</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="phones" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">mobile</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="phones" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">pager</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="phones" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">text</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="phones" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">textphone</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="phones" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">video</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="phones" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">voice</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="phones" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                </tbody>
              </table>
            </dd>
          </dl>
          <dl spacing="compact" newline="false" indent="20">
            <dt>Property Name:</dt>
            <dd>grammaticalGender</dd>
            <dt>Context:</dt>
            <dd>SpeakToAs</dd>
            <dt>Initial Contents:</dt>
            <dd>
              <table anchor="tab-iana-enum-speaktoas-grammaticalgender" align="left">
                <name>JSContact Enum Values for kind (Context: SpeakToAs)</name>
                <thead>
                  <tr>
                    <th align="left">Enum Value</th>
                    <th align="left">Reference or Description</th>
                  </tr>
                </thead>
                <tbody>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">animate</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="speakToAs" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">common</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="speakToAs" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">feminine</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="speakToAs" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">inanimate</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="speakToAs" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">masculine</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="speakToAs" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">neuter</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="speakToAs" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                </tbody>
              </table>
            </dd>
          </dl>
          <dl spacing="compact" newline="false" indent="20">
            <dt>Property Name:</dt>
            <dd>kind</dd>
            <dt>Context:</dt>
            <dd>AddressComponent</dd>
            <dt>Initial Contents:</dt>
            <dd>
              <table anchor="tab-iana-enum-addresscomponent-kind" align="left">
                <name>JSContact Enum Values for kind (Context: AddressComponent)</name>
                <thead>
                  <tr>
                    <th align="left">Enum Value</th>
                    <th align="left">Reference or Description</th>
                  </tr>
                </thead>
                <tbody>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">apartment</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="addresses" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">block</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="addresses" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">building</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="addresses" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">country</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="addresses" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">direction</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="addresses" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">district</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="addresses" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">floor</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="addresses" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">landmark</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="addresses" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">locality</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="addresses" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">name</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="addresses" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">number</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="addresses" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">postcode</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="addresses" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">postOfficeBox</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="addresses" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">region</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="addresses" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">room</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="addresses" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">separator</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="addresses" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">subdistrict</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="addresses" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                </tbody>
              </table>
            </dd>
          </dl>
          <dl spacing="compact" newline="false" indent="20">
            <dt>Property Name:</dt>
            <dd>kind</dd>
            <dt>Context:</dt>
            <dd>Anniversary</dd>
            <dt>Initial Contents:</dt>
            <dd>
              <table anchor="tab-iana-enum-anniversary-kind" align="left">
                <name>JSContact Enum Values for kind (Context: Anniversary)</name>
                <thead>
                  <tr>
                    <th align="left">Enum Value</th>
                    <th align="left">Reference or Description</th>
                  </tr>
                </thead>
                <tbody>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">birth</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="anniversaries" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">death</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="anniversaries" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">wedding</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="anniversaries" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                </tbody>
              </table>
            </dd>
          </dl>
          <dl spacing="compact" newline="false" indent="20">
            <dt>Property Name:</dt>
            <dd>kind</dd>
            <dt>Context:</dt>
            <dd>Calendar</dd>
            <dt>Initial Contents:</dt>
            <dd>
              <table anchor="tab-iana-enum-calendarresource-kind" align="left">
                <name>JSContact Enum Values for kind (Context: Calendar)</name>
                <thead>
                  <tr>
                    <th align="left">Enum Value</th>
                    <th align="left">Reference or Description</th>
                  </tr>
                </thead>
                <tbody>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">calendar</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="calendars" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">freeBusy</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="calendars" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                </tbody>
              </table>
            </dd>
          </dl>
          <dl spacing="compact" newline="false" indent="20">
            <dt>Property Name:</dt>
            <dd>kind</dd>
            <dt>Context:</dt>
            <dd>Card</dd>
            <dt>Initial Contents:</dt>
            <dd>
              <table anchor="tab-iana-enum-card-kind" align="left">
                <name>JSContact Enum Values for kind (Context: Card)</name>
                <thead>
                  <tr>
                    <th align="left">Enum Value</th>
                    <th align="left">Reference or Description</th>
                  </tr>
                </thead>
                <tbody>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">application</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="kind" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">device</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="kind" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">group</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="kind" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">individual</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="kind" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">location</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="kind" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">org</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="kind" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                </tbody>
              </table>
            </dd>
          </dl>
          <dl spacing="compact" newline="false" indent="20">
            <dt>Property Name:</dt>
            <dd>kind</dd>
            <dt>Context:</dt>
            <dd>Directory</dd>
            <dt>Initial Contents:</dt>
            <dd>
              <table anchor="tab-iana-enum-directoryresource-kind" align="left">
                <name>JSContact Enum Values for kind (Context: Directory)</name>
                <thead>
                  <tr>
                    <th align="left">Enum Value</th>
                    <th align="left">Reference or Description</th>
                  </tr>
                </thead>
                <tbody>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">directory</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="directories" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">entry</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="directories" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                </tbody>
              </table>
            </dd>
          </dl>
          <dl spacing="compact" newline="false" indent="20">
            <dt>Property Name:</dt>
            <dd>kind</dd>
            <dt>Context:</dt>
            <dd>Link</dd>
            <dt>Initial Contents:</dt>
            <dd>
              <table anchor="tab-iana-enum-linkresource-kind" align="left">
                <name>JSContact Enum Values for kind (Context: Link)</name>
                <thead>
                  <tr>
                    <th align="left">Enum Value</th>
                    <th align="left">Reference or Description</th>
                  </tr>
                </thead>
                <tbody>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">contact</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="links" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                </tbody>
              </table>
            </dd>
          </dl>
          <dl spacing="compact" newline="false" indent="20">
            <dt>Property Name:</dt>
            <dd>kind</dd>
            <dt>Context:</dt>
            <dd>Media</dd>
            <dt>Initial Contents:</dt>
            <dd>
              <table anchor="tab-iana-enum-mediaresource-kind" align="left">
                <name>JSContact Enum Values for kind (Context: Media)</name>
                <thead>
                  <tr>
                    <th align="left">Enum Value</th>
                    <th align="left">Reference or Description</th>
                  </tr>
                </thead>
                <tbody>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">logo</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="media" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">photo</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="media" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">sound</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="media" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                </tbody>
              </table>
            </dd>
          </dl>
          <dl spacing="compact" newline="false" indent="20">
            <dt>Property Name:</dt>
            <dd>kind</dd>
            <dt>Context:</dt>
            <dd>NameComponent</dd>
            <dt>Initial Contents:</dt>
            <dd>
              <table anchor="tab-iana-enum-namecomponent-kind" align="left">
                <name>JSContact Enum Values for kind (Context: NameComponent)</name>
                <thead>
                  <tr>
                    <th align="left">Enum Value</th>
                    <th align="left">Reference or Description</th>
                  </tr>
                </thead>
                <tbody>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">credential</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="name" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">generation</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="name" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">given</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="name" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">given2</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="name" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">separator</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="name" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">surname</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="name" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">surname2</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="name" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">title</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="name" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                </tbody>
              </table>
            </dd>
          </dl>
          <dl spacing="compact" newline="false" indent="20">
            <dt>Property Name:</dt>
            <dd>kind</dd>
            <dt>Context:</dt>
            <dd>PersonalInfo</dd>
            <dt>Initial Contents:</dt>
            <dd>
              <table anchor="tab-iana-enum-personalinformation-kind" align="left">
                <name>JSContact Enum Values for kind (Context: PersonalInfo)</name>
                <thead>
                  <tr>
                    <th align="left">Enum Value</th>
                    <th align="left">Reference or Description</th>
                  </tr>
                </thead>
                <tbody>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">expertise</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="personalInfo" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">hobby</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="personalInfo" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">interest</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="personalInfo" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                </tbody>
              </table>
            </dd>
          </dl>
          <dl spacing="compact" newline="false" indent="20">
            <dt>Property Name:</dt>
            <dd>kind</dd>
            <dt>Context:</dt>
            <dd>Title</dd>
            <dt>Initial Contents:</dt>
            <dd>
              <table anchor="tab-iana-enum-title-kind" align="left">
                <name>JSContact Enum Values for kind (Context: Title)</name>
                <thead>
                  <tr>
                    <th align="left">Enum Value</th>
                    <th align="left">Reference or Description</th>
                  </tr>
                </thead>
                <tbody>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">role</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="titles" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">title</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="titles" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                </tbody>
              </table>
            </dd>
          </dl>
          <dl spacing="compact" newline="false" indent="20">
            <dt>Property Name:</dt>
            <dd>level</dd>
            <dt>Context:</dt>
            <dd>PersonalInfo</dd>
            <dt>Initial Contents:</dt>
            <dd>
              <table anchor="tab-iana-enum-personalinformation-level" align="left">
                <name>JSContact Enum Values for level (Context: PersonalInfo)</name>
                <thead>
                  <tr>
                    <th align="left">Enum Value</th>
                    <th align="left">Reference or Description</th>
                  </tr>
                </thead>
                <tbody>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">high</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="personalInfo" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">low</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="personalInfo" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">medium</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="personalInfo" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                </tbody>
              </table>
            </dd>
          </dl>
          <dl spacing="compact" newline="false" indent="20">
            <dt>Property Name:</dt>
            <dd>relation</dd>
            <dt>Context:</dt>
            <dd>Relation</dd>
            <dt>Initial Contents:</dt>
            <dd>
              <table anchor="tab-iana-enum-relation-relation" align="left">
                <name>JSContact Enum Values for relation (Context: Relation)</name>
                <thead>
                  <tr>
                    <th align="left">Enum Value</th>
                    <th align="left">Reference or Description</th>
                  </tr>
                </thead>
                <tbody>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">acquaintance</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="relatedTo" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">agent</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="relatedTo" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">child</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="relatedTo" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">colleague</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="relatedTo" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">contact</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="relatedTo" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">co-resident</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="relatedTo" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">co-worker</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="relatedTo" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">crush</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="relatedTo" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">date</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="relatedTo" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">emergency</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="relatedTo" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">friend</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="relatedTo" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">kin</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="relatedTo" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">me</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="relatedTo" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">met</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="relatedTo" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">muse</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="relatedTo" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">neighbor</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="relatedTo" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">parent</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="relatedTo" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">sibling</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="relatedTo" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">spouse</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="relatedTo" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">sweetheart</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="relatedTo" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                </tbody>
              </table>
            </dd>
          </dl>
          <dl spacing="compact" newline="false" indent="20">
            <dt>Property Name:</dt>
            <dd>phoneticSystem</dd>
            <dt>Context:</dt>
            <dd>Address, Name</dd>
            <dt>Initial Contents:</dt>
            <dd>
              <table anchor="tab-iana-enum-pronounce-system" align="left">
                <name>JSContact Enum Values for system (Context: Address, Name)</name>
                <thead>
                  <tr>
                    <th align="left">Enum Value</th>
                    <th align="left">Reference or Description</th>
                  </tr>
                </thead>
                <tbody>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">ipa</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="prop-phonetic" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">jyut</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="prop-phonetic" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">piny</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="prop-phonetic" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                </tbody>
              </table>
            </dd>
          </dl>
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section anchor="security-considerations" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Security Considerations</name>
      <t>Contact information is very privacy-sensitive.  It can reveal the identity, location and credentials information, employment status, interests and hobbies, and social network of a user.  Its transmission and storage must be done carefully to protect it from possible threats, such as eavesdropping, replay, message insertion, deletion, modification, and on-path attacks.</t>
      <t>The data being stored and transmitted may be used in systems with real-world consequences.  For example, a malicious actor might provide JSContact data that uses the name of another person but insert their contact details to impersonate the unknown victim.  Such systems must be careful to authenticate all data they receive to prevent them from being subverted and ensure the change comes from an authorized entity.</t>
      <t>This document only defines the data format; such considerations are primarily the concern of the API or method of storage and transmission of such files.</t>
      <section anchor="json-parsing" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>JSON Parsing</name>
        <t>The security considerations of <xref target="RFC8259" format="default"/> apply to the use of JSON as the data interchange format.
    </t>
        <t>As for any serialization format, parsers need to thoroughly check the syntax of the supplied data.  JSON uses opening and closing brackets for several types and structures, and it is possible that the end of the supplied data will be reached when scanning for a matching closing bracket; this is an error condition, and implementations need to stop scanning at the end of the supplied data.</t>
        <t>JSON also uses a string encoding with some escape sequences to encode special characters within a string.  Care is needed when processing these escape sequences to ensure that they are fully formed before the special processing is triggered, with special care taken when the escape sequences appear adjacent to other (non-escaped) special characters or adjacent to the end of data (as in the previous paragraph).</t>
        <t>If parsing JSON into a non-textual structured data format, implementations may need to allocate storage to hold JSON string elements.  Since JSON does not use explicit string lengths, the risk of denial of service due to resource exhaustion is small, but implementations may still wish to place limits on the size of allocations they are willing to make in any given context, to avoid untrusted data causing excessive memory allocation.</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="uri-values" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>URI Values</name>
        <t>Several JSContact properties contain URIs as values, and processing these properties requires extra care.  <xref target="RFC3986" sectionFormat="of" section="7"/> discusses security risks related to URIs.</t>
        <t>Fetching remote resources carries inherent risks.  Connections must only be allowed on well-known ports, using allowed protocols (generally, just HTTP/HTTPS on their default ports).  The URL must be resolved externally and not allowed to access internal resources.  Connecting to an external source reveals IP (and therefore often location) information.</t>
        <t>A maliciously constructed JSContact object may contain a very large number of URIs.  In the case of published address books with a large number of subscribers, such objects could be widely distributed.  Implementations should be careful to limit the automatic fetching of linked resources to reduce the risk of this being an amplification vector for a denial-of-service attack.</t>
      </section>
    </section>
  </middle>
  <back>
    <references>
      <name>References</name>
      <references>
        <name>Normative References</name>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1034.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1035.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2046.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2426.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3339.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4122.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4648.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5234.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5322.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5646.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5870.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6350.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6901.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7493.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7529.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7942.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8126.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8141.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8174.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8259.xml"/>
        <reference anchor="ISO.3166-1.2006">
          <front>
            <title>Codes for the representation of names of countries, 3rd
              edition</title>
            <author>
              <organization>International Organization for
                Standardization</organization>
            </author>
            <date year="2006"/>
          </front>
          <seriesInfo name="ISO" value="Standard 3166-1"/>
        </reference>
        <reference anchor="IANATZ" target="https://www.iana.org/time-zones">
          <front>
            <title>IANA Time Zone Database</title>
            <author/>
          </front>
        </reference>
        <reference anchor="IANAvCard" target="https://www.iana.org/assignments/vcard-elements/vcard-elements.xhtml">
          <front>
            <title>IANA vCard Elements</title>
            <author/>
          </front>
        </reference>
      </references>
      <references>
        <name>Informative References</name>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3261.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3966.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3986.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6351.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6473.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6474.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6715.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6869.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7095.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8499.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8605.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-uuidrev-rfc4122bis.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-calext-jscontact.xml"/>
        <reference anchor="IPA" target="https://www.internationalphoneticalphabet.org/">
          <front>
            <title>International Phonetic Alphabet</title>
            <author/>
          </front>
        </reference>
        <reference anchor="UBiDi" target="https://www.unicode.org/reports/tr9/">
          <front>
            <title>Unicode® Standard Annex #9: Unicode Bidirectional Algorithm</title>
            <author/>
          </front>
        </reference>
      </references>
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
