<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!-- name="GENERATOR" content="github.com/mmarkdown/mmark Mmark Markdown Processor - mmark.miek.nl" -->
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM 'rfc2629.dtd' []>
<rfc ipr="trust200902" submissionType="IETF" category="std" xml:lang="en" consensus="yes" docName="draft-stepanek-jscontact-04">
<?rfc toc="yes"?><?rfc symrefs="yes"?><?rfc sortrefs="yes"?><?rfc compact="yes"?><?rfc subcompact="no"?><?rfc comments="no"?>
<front>
<title abbrev="JSContact">JSContact: A JSON representation of addressbook data</title><author initials="R." surname="Stepanek" fullname="Robert Stepanek"><organization>FastMail</organization><address><postal><street>PO Box 234, Collins St West</street>
<city>Melbourne</city>
<code>VIC 8007</code>
<country>Australia</country>
<region> </region>
</postal><email>rsto@fastmailteam.com</email>
</address></author>
<author initials="M." surname="Loffredo" fullname="Mario Loffredo"><organization>IIT-CNR</organization><address><postal><street>Via Moruzzi,1</street>
<city>Pisa</city>
<code>56124</code>
<country>Italy</country>
<region> </region>
</postal><email>mario.loffredo@iit.cnr.it</email>
</address></author>
<date year="2019" month="September" day="12"></date>
<area>Applications</area><workgroup>TBD</workgroup><keyword>JSON</keyword>
<keyword>addressbook</keyword>
<keyword>contacts</keyword>
<keyword>cards</keyword>
<keyword>VCARD</keyword>

<abstract><t>This specification defines a data model and JSON representation of contact card information that can be used for data storage and exchange in address book or directory applications. It aims to be an alternative to the vCard data format and to be unambiguous, extendable and simple to process. In contrast to the JSON-based jCard format, it is not a direct mapping from the vCard data model and expands semantics where appropriate.</t>
</abstract>

</front>

<middle>

<section anchor="introduction" title="Introduction">
<t>This document defines a data model for contact card data normally used in address book or directory applications and services. It aims to be an alternative to the vCard data format <xref target="RFC6350"></xref> and to provide a JSON-based standard representation of contact card data.</t>
<t>The key design considerations for this data model are as follows:</t>
<t>
<list style="symbols">
<t>Most of the initial set of attributes should be taken from the vCard data format <xref target="RFC6350"></xref> and extensions (<xref target="RFC6473"></xref>, <xref target="RFC6474"></xref>, <xref target="RFC6715"></xref>, <xref target="RFC6869"></xref>, <xref target="RFC8605"></xref>). The specification should add new attributes or value types, or not support existing ones, where appropriate. Conversion between the data formats need not fully preserve semantic meaning.</t>
<t>The attributes of the cards data represented must be described as a simple key-value pair, reducing complexity of its representation.</t>
<t>The data model should avoid all ambiguities and make it difficult to make mistakes during implementation.</t>
<t>Extensions, such as new properties and components, MUST NOT lead to requiring an update to this document.</t>
</list>
</t>
<t>The representation of this data model is defined in the I-JSON format <xref target="RFC7493"></xref>, which is a strict subset of the JavaScript Object Notation (JSON) Data Interchange Format <xref target="RFC8259"></xref>. Using JSON is mostly a pragmatic choice: its widespread use makes JSCard easier to adopt, and the availability of production-ready JSON implementations eliminates a whole category of parser-related interoperability issues.</t>

<section anchor="relation-to-the-xcard-and-jcard-formats" title="Relation to the xCard and jCard formats">
<t>The xCard <xref target="RFC6351"></xref> and jCard <xref target="RFC7095"></xref> specifications define alternative representations for vCard data, in XML and JSON format respectively. Both explicitly aim to not change the underlying data model. Accordingly, they are regarded as equal to vCard in the context of this document.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="terminology" title="Terminology">
<t>The key words &quot;MUST&quot;, &quot;MUST NOT&quot;, &quot;REQUIRED&quot;, &quot;SHALL&quot;, &quot;SHALL NOT&quot;, &quot;SHOULD&quot;,
&quot;SHOULD NOT&quot;, &quot;RECOMMENDED&quot;, &quot;NOT RECOMMENDED&quot;, &quot;MAY&quot;, and &quot;OPTIONAL&quot; in this
document are to be interpreted as described in BCP 14 <xref target="RFC2119"></xref> <xref target="RFC8174"></xref> when, and only when,
they appear in all capitals, as shown here.</t>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="jscard" title="JSCard">
<t>MIME type: <spanx style="verb">application/jscontact+json;type=jscard</spanx></t>
<t>A JSCard object stores information about a person, organization or company.</t>

<section anchor="metadata-properties" title="Metadata properties">

<section anchor="uid" title="uid">
<t>Type: <spanx style="verb">String</spanx> (mandatory).</t>
<t>An identifier, used to associate the object as the same across different systems, addressbooks and views.  <xref target="RFC4122"></xref> describes a range of established algorithms to generate universally unique identifiers (UUID), and the random or pseudo-random version is recommended.  For compatibility with <xref target="RFC6350"></xref> UIDs, implementations MUST accept both URI and free-form text.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="prodid" title="prodId">
<t>Type: <spanx style="verb">String</spanx> (optional).</t>
<t>The identifier for the product that created the JSCard object.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="updated" title="updated">
<t>Type: <spanx style="verb">String</spanx> (mandatory).</t>
<t>The date and time when the data in this JSCard object was last modified. The timestamp MUST be formatted as specified in <xref target="RFC3339"></xref>.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="kind" title="kind">
<t>Type: <spanx style="verb">String</spanx> (optional). The kind of the entity the Card represents.</t>
<t>The value MUST be either one of the following values, registered in a future RFC, or a vendor-specific value:</t>
<t>
<list style="symbols">
<t><spanx style="verb">individual</spanx>: a single person</t>
<t><spanx style="verb">org</spanx>: an organization</t>
<t><spanx style="verb">location</spanx>: a named location</t>
<t><spanx style="verb">device</spanx>: a device, such as appliances, computers, or network elements</t>
<t><spanx style="verb">application</spanx>: a software application</t>
</list>
</t>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="name-and-organization-properties" title="Name and Organization properties">

<section anchor="name" title="name">
<t>Type: Name (mandatory).</t>
<t>The name of the entity represented by this JSCard.  A Name object has the following properties:</t>
<t>
<list style="symbols">
<t>fullName: <spanx style="verb">LocalizedString</spanx> (mandatory).
The full name (e.g. the personal name and surname of an individual, the name of an organization) of the entity represented by this card.</t>
<t>prefix: <spanx style="verb">String[]</spanx> (optional).
The honorific title(s), e.g. <spanx style="verb">Mr</spanx>, <spanx style="verb">Ms</spanx>, <spanx style="verb">Dr</spanx>.</t>
<t>personalName: <spanx style="verb">String[]</spanx> (optional).
The personal name(s), also known as &quot;first name&quot;, &quot;give name&quot;.</t>
<t>surname: <spanx style="verb">String[]</spanx> (optional).
The surname(s) (also known as &quot;last name&quot;, &quot;family name&quot;).</t>
<t>additionalName: <spanx style="verb">String[]</spanx> (optional).
The additional name(s), also known as &quot;middle name&quot;.</t>
<t>suffix: <spanx style="verb">String[]</spanx> (optional).
The honorific suffix(es), e.g. <spanx style="verb">B.A.</spanx>, <spanx style="verb">Esq.</spanx>.</t>
<t>nickname: <spanx style="verb">String[]</spanx> (optional).
The nickname(s) of the person represented by this card.</t>
</list>
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="organization" title="organization">
<t>Type: <spanx style="verb">LocalizedString[]</spanx> (optional).</t>
<t>The company or organization name and units associated with this card.
The first entry in the list names the organization, and any following
entries name organizational units.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="jobtitle" title="jobTitle">
<t>Type : <spanx style="verb">LocalizedString[]</spanx> (optional).</t>
<t>The job title(s) or functional position(s) of the entity represented by this card.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="role" title="role">
<t>Type : <spanx style="verb">LocalizedString[]</spanx> (optional).</t>
<t>The role(s), function(s) or part(s) played in a particular situation by the entity represented by this card. In contrast to a job title, the roles might differ for example in project contexts.</t>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="contact-and-resource-properties" title="Contact and Resource properties">

<section anchor="emails" title="emails">
<t>Type: <spanx style="verb">Resource[]</spanx> (optional).</t>
<t>An array of Resource objects where the values are URLs in the <xref target="RFC6068"></xref> <spanx style="verb">mailto</spanx> scheme or free-text email addresses. Types are:</t>
<t>
<list style="symbols">
<t><spanx style="verb">personal</spanx> The address is for emailing in a personal context.</t>
<t><spanx style="verb">work</spanx> The address is for emailing in a professional context.</t>
<t><spanx style="verb">other</spanx> The address is for some other purpose. A label property MAY be included to display next to the address to help the user identify its purpose.</t>
</list>
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="phones" title="phones">
<t>Type: <spanx style="verb">Resource[]</spanx> (optional).</t>
<t>An array of Resource objects where the values are URIs scheme or free-text phone numbers. Typical URI schemes are the <xref target="RFC3966"></xref> <spanx style="verb">tel</spanx> or <xref target="RFC3261"></xref> <spanx style="verb">sip</spanx> schemes, but any URI scheme is allowed. Resource types are:</t>
<t>
<list style="symbols">
<t><spanx style="verb">voice</spanx> The number is for calling by voice.</t>
<t><spanx style="verb">fax</spanx> The number is for sending faxes.</t>
<t><spanx style="verb">pager</spanx> The number is for a pager or beeper.</t>
<t><spanx style="verb">other</spanx> The number is for some other purpose. A label property MAY be included to display next to the number to help the user identify its purpose.</t>
</list>
</t>
<t>The following labels are pre-defined for phone resources:</t>
<t>
<list style="symbols">
<t><spanx style="verb">private</spanx> The phone number should be used in a private context.</t>
<t><spanx style="verb">work</spanx> The phone number should be used in a professional context</t>
</list>
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="online" title="online">
<t>Type: <spanx style="verb">Resource[]</spanx> (optional).</t>
<t>An array of Resource objects where the values are URIs or usernames associated with the card for online services.
Types are:</t>
<t>
<list style="symbols">
<t><spanx style="verb">uri</spanx> The value is a URI, e.g. a website link.</t>
<t><spanx style="verb">username</spanx> The value is a username associated with the entity represented by this card (e.g. for social media, or an IM client). A label property SHOULD be included to identify what service this is for. For compatibility between clients, this label SHOULD be the canonical service name, including capitalisation. e.g. <spanx style="verb">Twitter</spanx>, <spanx style="verb">Facebook</spanx>, <spanx style="verb">Skype</spanx>, <spanx style="verb">GitHub</spanx>, <spanx style="verb">XMPP</spanx>.</t>
<t><spanx style="verb">other</spanx> The value is something else not covered by the above categories. A label property MAY be included to display next to the number to help the user identify its purpose.</t>
</list>
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="preferredcontactmethod" title="preferredContactMethod">
<t>Type : <spanx style="verb">String</spanx> (optional)</t>
<t>Defines the preferred contact method or resource with additional information about this card. The value MUST be the property name of one of the Resource lists: <spanx style="verb">emails</spanx>, <spanx style="verb">phones</spanx>, <spanx style="verb">online</spanx>, <spanx style="verb">other</spanx>.</t>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="address-and-location-properties" title="Address and Location properties">

<section anchor="addresses" title="addresses">
<t>Type: Address[] (optional).</t>
<t>An array of Address objects, containing physical locations. An Address object has the following properties:</t>
<t>
<list style="symbols">
<t>type: <spanx style="verb">String</spanx> (mandatory).
Specifies the context of the address information.
The value MUST be either one of the following values, registered in a future
RFC, or a vendor-specific value:
<list style="symbols">
<t><spanx style="verb">home</spanx> An address of a residence.</t>
<t><spanx style="verb">work</spanx> An address of a workplace.</t>
<t><spanx style="verb">billing</spanx> An address to be used for billing.</t>
<t><spanx style="verb">postal</spanx> An address to be used for delivering physical items.</t>
<t><spanx style="verb">other</spanx> An address not covered by the above categories.</t>
</list></t>
<t>label: <spanx style="verb">String</spanx> (optional).
A label describing the value in more detail.</t>
<t>fullAddress: <spanx style="verb">LocalizedString</spanx> (optional).
The complete address, excluding type and label. This property is mainly useful to represent addresses of which the individual address components are unknown, or to provide localized representations.</t>
<t>street: <spanx style="verb">String</spanx> (optional).
The street address. This MAY be multiple lines; newlines MUST be preserved.</t>
<t>extension: <spanx style="verb">String</spanx> (optional)
The extended address, such as an apartment or suite number, or care-of address.</t>
<t>locality: <spanx style="verb">String</spanx> (optional).
The city, town, village, post town, or other locality within which the street address may be found.</t>
<t>region: <spanx style="verb">String</spanx> (optional).
The province, such as a state, county, or canton within which the locality may be found.</t>
<t>country: <spanx style="verb">String</spanx> (optional).
The country name.</t>
<t>postOfficeBox: <spanx style="verb">String</spanx> (optional)
The post office box.</t>
<t>postcode: <spanx style="verb">String</spanx> (optional).
The postal code, post code, ZIP code or other short code associated with the address by the relevant country's postal system.</t>
<t>countryCode: <spanx style="verb">String</spanx> (optional).
The ISO-3166-1 country code.</t>
<t>coordinates: <spanx style="verb">String</spanx> (optional) A <xref target="RFC5870"></xref> &quot;geo:&quot; URI for the address.</t>
<t>timeZone: <spanx style="verb">String</spanx> (optional) Identifies the time zone this address is located in. This SHOULD be a time zone name registered in the <eref target="https://www.iana.org/time-zones">IANA Time Zone Database</eref>. Unknown time zone identifiers MAY be ignored by implementations.</t>
<t>isPreferred: Boolean (optional, default: false).
Whether this Address is the preferred for its type. This SHOULD only be one per type.</t>
</list>
</t>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="additional-properties" title="Additional properties">

<section anchor="anniversaries" title="anniversaries">
<t>Type : Anniversary[] (optional).</t>
<t>Memorable dates and events for the entity represented by this card. An Anniversary object has the following properties:</t>
<t>
<list style="symbols">
<t>type: <spanx style="verb">String</spanx> (mandatory).
Specifies the type of the anniversary. This RFC predefines the following types, but implementations MAY use additional values:
<list style="symbols">
<t><spanx style="verb">birth</spanx>: a birth day anniversary</t>
<t><spanx style="verb">death</spanx>: a death day anniversary</t>
<t><spanx style="verb">other</spanx>: an anniversary not covered by any of the known types.</t>
</list></t>
<t>date: <spanx style="verb">String</spanx> (mandatory).
The date of this anniversary, in the form &quot;YYYY-MM-DD&quot; (any part may be all 0s for unknown) or a <xref target="RFC3339"></xref> timestamp.</t>
<t>place: Address (optional).
An address associated with this anniversary, e.g. the place of birth or death.</t>
</list>
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="personalinfo" title="personalInfo">
<t>Type: PersonalInformation[] (optional).</t>
<t>A list of personal information about the entity represented by this card.
A PersonalInformation object has the following properties:</t>
<t>
<list style="symbols">
<t>type: <spanx style="verb">String</spanx> (mandatory).
Specifies the type for this personal information. Allowed values are:
<list style="symbols">
<t><spanx style="verb">expertise</spanx>: a field of expertise or credential</t>
<t><spanx style="verb">hobby</spanx>: a hobby</t>
<t><spanx style="verb">interest</spanx>: an interest</t>
<t><spanx style="verb">other</spanx>: an information not covered by the above categories</t>
</list></t>
<t>value: <spanx style="verb">String</spanx> (mandatory).
The actual information. This generally is free-text, but future specifications MAY restrict allowed values depending on the type of this PersonalInformation.</t>
<t>level: <spanx style="verb">String</spanx> (optional)
Indicates the level of expertise, or engagement in hobby or interest. Allowed values are: <spanx style="verb">high</spanx>, <spanx style="verb">medium</spanx> and <spanx style="verb">low</spanx>.</t>
</list>
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="notes" title="notes">
<t>Type: <spanx style="verb">LocalizedString[]</spanx> (optional).</t>
<t>Arbitrary notes about the entity represented by this card.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="categories" title="categories">
<t>Type: <spanx style="verb">String[]</spanx> (optional).
A list of free-text or URI categories that relate to the card.</t>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="common-jscard-types" title="Common JSCard types">

<section anchor="localized-string-type" title="LocalizedString">
<t>A LocalizedString object has the following properties:</t>
<t>
<list style="symbols">
<t>value: <spanx style="verb">String</spanx> (mandatory).
The property value.</t>
<t>language: <spanx style="verb">String</spanx> (optional).
The <xref target="RFC5646"></xref> language tag of this value, if any.</t>
<t>localizations: <spanx style="verb">String[String]</spanx> (optional).
A map from <xref target="RFC5646"></xref> language tags to the value localized in that language.</t>
</list>
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="resource-type" title="Resource">
<t>A Resource object has the following properties:</t>
<t>
<list style="symbols">
<t>type: <spanx style="verb">String</spanx> (mandatory).
Specifies the context of the resource. This MUST be taken from the set of values specified for the respective property.</t>
<t>label: <spanx style="verb">String</spanx> (optional).
A label describing the value in more detail, especially if the type property has value <spanx style="verb">other</spanx> (but MAY be included with any type).</t>
<t>value: <spanx style="verb">String</spanx> (mandatory).
The actual resource value, e.g. an email address or phone number.</t>
<t>mediaType: <spanx style="verb">String</spanx> (optional).
Used for properties with URI values. Provides the media type <xref target="RFC2046"></xref> of the resource identified by the URI.</t>
<t>isPreferred: Boolean (optional, default: false).
Whether this resource is the preferred for its type. This SHOULD only be one per type.</t>
</list>
</t>
</section>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="jscardgroup" title="JSCardGroup">
<t>MIME type: <spanx style="verb">application/jscontact+json;type=jscardgroup</spanx></t>
<t>A JSCardGroup object represents a named set of JSCards.</t>

<section anchor="properties" title="Properties">

<section anchor="uid-1" title="uid">
<t>Type : <spanx style="verb">String</spanx> (mandatory).</t>
<t>A globally unique identifier. The same requirements as for the JSCard uid property apply.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="name-1" title="name">
<t>Type: <spanx style="verb">String</spanx> (optional).</t>
<t>The user-visible name for the group, e.g. &quot;Friends&quot;. This may be any UTF-8 string of at least 1 character in length and maximum 255 octets in size. The same name may be used by two different groups.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="cardids" title="cardIds">
<t>Type : <spanx style="verb">String[]</spanx> (mandatory).
The ids of the cards in the group. Implementations MUST preserve the order of list entries.</t>
</section>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="implementation-status" title="Implementation Status">
<t>NOTE: Please remove this section and the reference to <xref target="RFC7942"></xref> prior
to publication as an RFC.
This section records the status of known implementations of the
protocol defined by this specification at the time of posting of this
Internet-Draft, and is based on a proposal described in
<xref target="RFC7942"></xref>. The description of implementations in this section is
intended to assist the IETF in its decision processes in progressing
drafts to RFCs. Please note that the listing of any individual
implementation here does not imply endorsement by the IETF.
Furthermore, no effort has been spent to verify the information
presented here that was supplied by IETF contributors. This is not
intended as, and must not be construed to be, a catalog of available
implementations or their features. Readers are advised to note that
other implementations may exist.
According to <xref target="RFC7942"></xref>, &quot;this will allow reviewers and working groups
to assign due consideration to documents that have the benefit of
running code, which may serve as evidence of valuable experimentation
and feedback that have made the implemented protocols more mature.
It is up to the individual working groups to use this information as
they see fit&quot;.</t>

<section anchor="iit-cnr-registro-it" title="IIT-CNR/Registro.it">
<t>
<list style="symbols">
<t>Responsible Organization: Institute of Informatics and Telematics
of National Research Council (IIT-CNR)/Registro.it</t>
<t>Location: <eref target="https://rdap.pubtest.nic.it/">https://rdap.pubtest.nic.it/</eref></t>
<t>Description: This implementation includes support for RDAP queries
using data from the public test environment of .it ccTLD. The
RDAP server does not implement any security policy because data
returned by this server are only for experimental testing
purposes. The RDAP server returns responses including JSCard in place of jCard when queries contain the parameter jscard=1.</t>
<t>Level of Maturity: This is a &quot;proof of concept&quot; research implementation.</t>
<t>Coverage: This implementation includes all of the features described in this specification.</t>
<t>Contact Information: Mario Loffredo, mario.loffredo@iit.cnr.it</t>
</list>
</t>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="iana-considerations" title="IANA Considerations">
<t>TBD</t>
</section>

<section anchor="security-considerations" title="Security Considerations">
<t>TBD</t>
</section>

</middle>

<back>
<references title="Normative References">
<?rfc include="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6351.xml"?>
<?rfc include="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7095.xml"?>
<?rfc include="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4122.xml"?>
<?rfc include="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5870.xml"?>
<?rfc include="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2046.xml"?>
<?rfc include="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5646.xml"?>
<?rfc include="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6350.xml"?>
<?rfc include="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8259.xml"?>
<?rfc include="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml"?>
<?rfc include="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7942.xml"?>
<?rfc include="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7493.xml"?>
<?rfc include="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8174.xml"?>
</references>
<references title="Informative References">
<?rfc include="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6068.xml"?>
<?rfc include="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6473.xml"?>
<?rfc include="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6869.xml"?>
<?rfc include="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3339.xml"?>
<?rfc include="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3966.xml"?>
<?rfc include="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3261.xml"?>
<?rfc include="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6715.xml"?>
<?rfc include="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6474.xml"?>
<?rfc include="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8605.xml"?>
</references>

</back>

</rfc>
